<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The loves and adventures of Clerio &amp; Lozia. a romance. Written originally in French, and translated into English by Fra. Kirkman, Gent.</title>
            <author>Du Périer, Antoine.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 201 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 96 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88621</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3260</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1289_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202767</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862949</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862949</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115129</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88621)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115129)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 173:E1289[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The loves and adventures of Clerio &amp; Lozia. a romance. Written originally in French, and translated into English by Fra. Kirkman, Gent.</title>
                  <author>Du Périer, Antoine.</author>
                  <author>Kirkman, Francis, 1632-ca. 1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 160, 177-198 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.M. and are to be sold by William Ley, at his shop at Pauls Chain,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Du Périer, Antoine.  Les amours de Lozie.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The loves and adventures of Clerio and Lozia.</note>
                  <note>Variant: quire M in another imposition; pagination [8], 175, 192-198.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug. 3.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115129:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LOVES AND ADVENTVRES OF <hi>CLERIO</hi> &amp; <hi>LOZIA.</hi>
A ROMANCE.</p>
            <p>Written Originally in French, and Tranſlated into Engliſh By
<hi>Fra. Kirkman,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. M.</hi> and are to be ſold by
<hi>William Ley,</hi> at his ſhop at <hi>Pauls</hi> Chain. 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:115129:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115129:2"/>
            <head>TO His much honored Friend WIL. BEESTON,
<abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Ivers times (in my hearing) to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of the whol
Company, you have moſt judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly diſcourſed of Poëſie: which
is the cauſe J preſume to chuſe you for my Patron and Protector; who are
the happiest interpretor and judg <pb facs="tcp:115129:3"/>of our Engliſh Stage-Playes
this Nation ever produced; which the Poets and Actors of theſe times, cannot
(with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ingratitude) deny; for J have heard the chief, and moſt ingenious
of them, acknowledg their Fames &amp; Profits eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially ſprung from
your inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, judgment and fancy. J am vers'd in Forraign tongues and
ſubſcribe to your opinion, that no Nation ever could glory in ſuch
Playes, as the moſt learned and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perable <hi>Johnſon,</hi> the copious
<pb facs="tcp:115129:3"/>
               <hi>Shakeſpear,</hi> or the ingenuous <hi>Fletcher</hi> compos'd;
but J be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve the French for amorous language, admirable inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, high
atchievements, hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Loves inimitable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, are not to be
equalled: and that no Nation yeilds better Arguments for Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance Playes (the
onely Poëms now deſired) then the French: Therefore, and for you have I
tranſlated the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures and Loves of <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio</hi> and <hi>Lozia;</hi>
and I doubt not though they fail to receive <pb facs="tcp:115129:4"/>incouragement from you,
your ſon, Mr <hi>George Beeſton</hi> (whom knowing men conclude, a hopeful
inheritor of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers rare ingenuity) may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them with a gracious
al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance.</p>
            <p>And ſir, though the work be not entirely happy in your
conſtruction (for my years are not arrived to knowledg to add where the
Author wants matter, or to leſſen where he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds) yet you will find much
newneſs in the Story, worthy an excellent Poët to inſoul it for 
<pb facs="tcp:115129:4"/>the Stage; where it wil receive ful perfection equal to the
am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The conſtant admirer of your Excellent Parts, <hi>Fra.
Kirkman,</hi> jun.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:115129:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115129:5"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Loves</hi> and <hi>Adventures</hi> OF CLERIO and
LOZIA.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Fortune of Man is an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure riddle, which Time only the
moſt Orthodox Interpretor of the Heavens, of the Gods, and Nature, can truely
explicate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Ladies!</hi> The Fortune of the Famous <hi>Clerio</hi> and
the fair <hi>Lozia,</hi> whoſe lives and loves are both delineated in this
inſuing Hiſtory, I preſent to you, with this perſwaſion, That as a
pleaſant Land-skip it will yeild ſome ſmall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment to your mindes,
and recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unto your Spirits. In the Deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of whoſe variable
conditions, I will <pb n="2" facs="tcp:115129:6"/>firſt begin with <hi>Clerio,</hi> whom
with my pen I will portrait before your eyes, as our chiefeſt and
choiſeſt Judges.</p>
            <p>This young Gentleman from his youth being indued with courage, and
induced by curioſitie, went abroad into Forraign parts, to ſee the
cuſtoms of thoſe places, to add by induſtry ſome higher degree of
perfection to that which Nature, amorous of him, had ſo freely beſtowed
upon him: After he had ſeen <hi>Germany</hi> and the Eaſtern Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries he
ſtayed three whole years in <hi>Italy</hi> where he was accounted ſo
perfect and exact in all ſorts of exerciſes becoming a Gentleman, that it
was impoſſible to finde any man more perfectly accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed then
himſelf. This Merchant for honour, having made a ſucceſsfull ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture,
returned home to the Court full fraught both with glory and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown, which
(durſt I ſay ſo) was empty during his abſence, of the greateſt part
of its ſplendor, who was not like a ſtar of the firſt Magnitude ſhining
brightly in the firmament there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <pb n="3" facs="tcp:115129:6"/>but as a glorious Sun,
whoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence brought a day, and whoſe abſence a night, upon the
Horizon of the Court, which did not only inlighten it, but ſlid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the
eyes it crept into the hearts of the faireſt Ladies the Court afforded, who
at the firſt ſight of ſo lovely a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, were wonderfully enamored of
him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clerio</hi> not ſetling the circumference of his deſires
in the center of any of their hearts, which were ſo deſirous of his, but as
a triumphant Conqueror carried al theirs captives into <hi>Spain,</hi> leaving
them behind to bemoan their miſery in ſo happy yet unhappy affections,
where alſo he murthered a Million of innocent lovers by an over-rigid
diſdain of their beauties: but they were ſoon avenged on him for this
rigorous dealing; for not long after he became exceedingly in love with the
Princeſs <hi>Lozia</hi> who was young, rich, and very beautiful, equally
adorned with pulchritude in her face, and perfection of parts in her mind. And
although <hi>Clerio</hi> was a gentleman <pb n="4" facs="tcp:115129:7"/>but worth fifteen
thouſand Francs of revenue, yet did he undertake to ſerve ſo noble a
Princeſs, who ſince the deceaſe of her Father and Mother, was under the
Gardianſhip of the Duke of <hi>Blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi> her Uncle, who intended to
match her to the Duke of <hi>Doudonne</hi> his Son, and for fear any other
ſhould eſpouſe her, he watched her ſo narrowly above the common
cuſtome of the Country both with <hi>Argo's</hi> and with <hi>Lynk's</hi>
eyes, and kept her within ſo ſtraitned limits, that if <hi>Clerio</hi>
could by chance ſee her, yet could by no means come to ſpeak to her. Fill'd
with love and deſpair he did ſo diligently inquire and carefully pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue
his deſired wiſhes, that at laſt he came to know her Lady of honour,
which was named <hi>Vincia,</hi> and was a French Gentlewoman, the death of
whoſe husband did ſo exceedingly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict her, that ſhe was conſtrained
to ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh her ſelf by a voluntary exile into <hi>Spain. Clerio</hi> being
very joyfull of this news procured the ſight of her, whom at the firſt view
he knew not, although <pb n="5" facs="tcp:115129:7"/>ſhe was his neer Kinſwoman,
becauſe he had not lately ſeen her, and which was the ſtrangeſt, ſhe
was acoutred after the Spaniſh faſhion; but <hi>in fine</hi> after a
thouſand hearty congratulations and welcome imbracements they promiſed to
owe each the other ſo much ſervice and affection, that under this pretext
<hi>Clerio</hi> viſited <hi>Vincia</hi> every day, not ſo much becauſe
his reſpects unto his Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin did oblige him thereto, as he was drawn
thither by the attractive load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of lovely <hi>Lozia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Moon had ſix ſeverall times re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived its borrowed light
before <hi>Clerio</hi> durſt diſcover unto his Couſin that affection
which he bore to her Miſtreſs; but at laſt not being able to reſiſt
thoſe fervent flames that the eyes, thoſe two glorious Suns of that famous
Princeſs had kindled in his heart; meeting one day with <hi>Vincia</hi> in
the Garden, thus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boarded her.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vincia,</hi> do not you know, ſeeing my countenance altered
and my face ſo wan, that there is alſo a change in my <pb n="6" facs="tcp:115129:8"/>heart, which appeareth thus upon my brows, and that if you were very
quick ſighted and had but a window to open into my heart you would ſee the
Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of love ſo deeply ingraven thereon, that the very peruſall of
them would ſufficiently acquaint you with my dolefull condition:
<hi>Vincia</hi> being overtaken with ſorrow and impatience interrupted his
diſcourſe; ſaying,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clerio,</hi> I never had ſo ſenſible an apprehenſion
of any afflictions as of that which your dolorous ſpeeches have cauſed in
my heart: alas, whence hath ſo ſudden a change as ſince yeſterday
happened to you? I intreat you to caſe my drooping Spirit of that weight of
ſorrow which your ſilence hath laid upon it by the continuation of your
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and conceal not any thing from ſo ſure a friend as I am,
whoſe love will make any enterpriſe, be it never ſo difficult or
dangerous, both facile and delightfull, to gratifie ſo noble a Spirit as
yours. My dear Couſin, I do not eſteem any thing ſo much, of all that I 
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115129:8"/>have brought with me into this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, but it ſhall be
ſubordinate to plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or to profit your good grace: there is none of all
my kindred whom I affect or honour more then your ſelf; believe that if the
loſs of all my means with my life it ſelf, might but redeem the leaſt
part of your loſt delights, I ſhal eſteem my ſelf to live in dying, if
my death can procure that contentment to you which hath been denyed to my
miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble life.</p>
            <p>Oh <hi>Vincia,</hi> ſaid <hi>Clerio,</hi> ſix moneths at
leaſt are paſſed ſince I was firſt amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of the moſt pure and
perfect beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that ever the ſun beheld, and do you account of this but as a
day? My Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin pardon me I beſeech you, for I did ſuppoſe ſome
ſudden accident had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to you ſince I ſaw your honour, for you have
ever covered your amorous dolour under colour of a certain diſeaſe
wherewith you were tormented, this you know; but pray honour me ſo far as to
tell me what Lady you bear ſo great affection to?</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:115129:9"/>
            <p>'Tis with <hi>Lozia</hi> my dear Couſin, which name is forced by
mine extream paſſion to bee pronounced with my mouth, as her glorious
beauty hath ſtamped it with an indelible character upon my heart.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lozia,</hi> my Couſin! I ſhould rather have beleeved the
moſt impoſſible things in the world to be feaſible then this to be
true; ſhame and death could not have given you ſo inſenſible a
ſenſe of your miſhap, as in the love of ſo fair an object: know you not
that the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Princeſſes are as the beams of the Sun, which we muſt
look on in an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique line with admiration, not in a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect line, with
deſire of poſſeſſion; for when we are drawing nearer to ſo
da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeling a light, and farther from our own, we muſt ſtiffe thoſe
venomous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires in the firſt motions of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, for fear they
prove Vipers to our ſouls, and in their birth break through the bellies of
their mothers, and ſo draw the firſt begining of their lives from the
miſerable end of ours.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:115129:9"/>
            <p>I knew well enough, replyed he, that you would think it ſtrange
that I, who have the reputation of an underſtanding man, have been ſo weak
as to let ſo ſtrong a paſſion get ſo powerful an head. If on the
other ſide you conſider not that Nature hath ſo perfectly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed
her, that ſhe ſubjugates the reaſon and the ſoul of all who ſee her
to ſerve her. I had thought after I had been a year in <hi>Spain</hi> to
return again into mine own Country, but her beauty, gifts and graces are ſuch
ſtrong Anchors, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter twenty years they will ſtill hold me faſt at
her feet, notwithſtanding all the ſtorms and tempeſts which
diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and deſpairs can ſtir up in the ſea of my Soul: I will
wait for a quiet calm from the honour of her good grace, and the ceſſation
of my ſorrows by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſition of your favorable endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clerio</hi> (quoth <hi>Vincia</hi>) I am in a ſtrait, and
know not what to do; if I forſake you, I foreſee your deſtruction; if I
aſſiſt you, I do but mingle my ruine with <pb n="10" facs="tcp:115129:10"/>yours. But
as the ſaying is, <hi>Good blood can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not lye, but muſt in the afflictions
of friends needs diſcover it ſelf:</hi> ſo do I already perceive it
running to my heart to change thoſe icy fears that are there congealed of any
peril into ſo many flames of love and aſſurance of ſucceſs, for the
obtaining of which I will em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy my utmoſt abilities, even to the loſs of
my life, in obedience to your Commandments. I know that the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Ladies
move indifferently the paſſions of men, and that being ſtirred up, they
drown the greateſt part of the gallanteſt perſons by their mercileſs
ſurges. Therefore my Couſin, ſhould we rather ſeek to ſave you from
this Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack, then to remain in the bemoaning of your miſery, which in
tract of time will bring forth a greater? You are not the firſt which hath
been in love with Queens and Princeſſes. There have been an infinite number
of them which had neither the half of your ſpirit nor your merit, who in the
end by patience and diſcretion have attained to the <pb n="11" facs="tcp:115129:10"/>heighth of their deſires. Hiſtories are full of ſuch
paſſages, as you know, who are not ignorant of any thing which concerneth
the perfection of a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: But if it ſeem good to you, I give you this
as mine advice; That you feign that you are in love with me, &amp; that you
employ, every one, as you ſhal ſee oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, to perform any friendly
office in that behalf, and often write letters to me, that removing all
ſuſpicion, you may ſee your Lady every day under colour of viſiting me,
and I will ſtamp ſo good an impreſſion of your merits upon her, that
with the good opinion which ſhe alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy hath of your honour, I hope it will
be an eaſie matter to make her love you; ſhe is yet a child, and nothing
more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie then to bend her heart to our deſires: No body underſtands
our language; I lie in the chamber with her, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſhe honours me
ſo much, as to let me lie in the bed with her, and that you know is the place
where Souls have the moſt free aſſociation; therefore there will I
diſcourſe of your great love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <pb n="12" facs="tcp:115129:11"/>me, and will
beſtow ſo many en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comiums of praiſe upon your honour, that by force ſhe
ſhall willingly affect you; and when I ſee her never ſo little inclined
towards you, I will endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor to engage her ſo deeply in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize,
that ſhe ſhall be able to do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which I ſhall not firſt approve
of, for of neceſſity ſhe muſt come to me to be her Counſellor, and
then what iſſue your affairs will come to, judg you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vincia,</hi> ſaid <hi>Clerio,</hi> the aſſurance of your
affection is that wherein I place the ſureneſs of my ambitious love, which
giveth me as much hope and confidence of ſucceſs, as I can have
di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt from the thoughts of her great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the apprehenſion of
the ſmall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of my deſerts.</p>
            <p>My Couſin, quoth <hi>Vincia,</hi> time doth now call me to
depart, and waite upon my Miſtreſs to Church, and ſhe without queſtion
will queſtion me concerning what we have diſcourſed all this while, which
wil be a very opportune occaſion <pb n="13" facs="tcp:115129:11"/>for me to ſpeak to her
concerning you, but be ſure you fail not to come to me on a viſit of
reſpect after dinner. After <hi>Vincia</hi> had given her Miſtreſs the
good morrow, with a pleaſant ſmile ſhe gave her her Fan: <hi>Lozia</hi>
being of a courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſpoſition, doubting this was for ſome unhappy
accident, asked her the occaſion of it, but the other being at this time to
play the cuning woman, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to tell her, to make the relation go the
better, and after an infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of excuſes and evaſions, being as it
were unable to deny her intreaties, or rather diſobey her deſirous
commands, ſaid, Miſtreſs, I cannot but laugh to think of the
diſcourſes I and my Couſin have had together this two houres in the
Garden, concerning the great love he bears to me. He offered me his ſervice
with the eleganteſt words that I ever heard; but I am ſorry either that he
is ſo much in love with me, or that I am ſo neerly akin to him: for he is a
moſt gallant gentleman, and I beleeve a gentlewoman will be ſerved as
wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily <pb n="14" facs="tcp:115129:12"/>thily by him as by any man in the world. He is
ſo perfectly accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that there is no ſort of exerciſe in which
he is not very expert: He is a brave Dancer, a good Horſeman, and ſpeaks
moſt learnedly, hath been a great traveller, is diſcreet, courteous,
beautiful, and as perfect as Nature could poſſibly make him: Would to God
that he were but as paſſionately affected for ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whoſe parts
and graces did in ſome ſort bear proportion to his.</p>
            <p>But wherefore will not you love him, quoth <hi>Lozia?</hi> I will
procure a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe for you from M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Cardinal,</hi> mine Uncle, to marry
him. If I could but meet with one of my quality, which is like to him, I would
make more account of him then ſo. You ſee that they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to marry me to
my couſin, which at the beſt is but a ſot: therein is the condition of
you, other gentlewomen, more happy then ours, ſeeing you have the choyce of
thoſe perſons which you like beſt of. But we, which are above the
ordinary ſort of people, either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <pb n="15" facs="tcp:115129:12"/>come fools in
following our own phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſies and inclinations in our young days, or elſe
we muſt wait till we are old for ſome party whoſe means is ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to
ours; and if there can be ſuch a one found in ten Kingdoms, though not a man
but a little better then a beaſt, we muſt be eſpouſed to him, and
ſpend the reſidue of our days without any pleaſure with them:
<hi>Vincia,</hi> I find him ſo amiable, that I counſel thee to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
him courteouſly.</p>
            <p>Whileſt <hi>Vincia</hi> was in diſcourſe with the beautiful
<hi>Lozia, Clerio</hi> ſpoke to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, advantaged by his vain
imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons concerning his love, whereby had it not been that he had had
ſome confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in his Couſin, he would have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt kill'd himſelf
with his own fears, which were his greateſt enemies: Now imagining that
<hi>Lozia</hi> would never ſtoop ſo low as to love him, then doubting his
deſign might be diſcovered, and ſo both of them endangered, arguing thus
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt himſelf to his utmoſt ability, he had almoſt diſarmed
himſelf of all his <pb n="16" facs="tcp:115129:13"/>hope, and given his love up at leaſt
for loſt: But whileſt he was floating upon the waves of theſe
diſtracted irreſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the time of the aſſignation ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached,
wherein he was to viſit his Love, for which end he dreſſed himſelf
after the French faſhion; his Hoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened with black, the Doublet with
white Satten cut, doubled with fillets of Gold and coller of Amber, with a
Chain of Musk hanging by a Ribbon five dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, upon the which was faſtened a
fair picture; his head comely, and beſtrued with <hi>Cyprus</hi> powder; his
Beard and Hair ſhining like the radiant <hi>Phebus,</hi> the eyes and
features of his vizage fair, his hand and favour extreamly beauteous, he had
Gloves perfum'd, his Colloſhoo's of Velvet, his Hat was ombraged with a plume
of black Herons Feathers, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with an enſign of Diamonds, which gave as
great a luſter to his fair vizage, as the Sun in the Meridian; a Mantle of
Velvet cut upon black, and half cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with little bands of Satten,
compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly faſhioned; his Girdle embroidered <pb n="17" facs="tcp:115129:13"/>with Gold,
his Sword with the gards of Milan.</p>
            <p>Being attired after this faſhion, the moſt common, and counted
the moſt comely in that time, accompanied with two Gentlemen, two Pages, and
four Lacquies very neatly dreſſed; he went towards the Palace of his
beautiful <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zia,</hi> at whoſe gate he ſacrificed a ſigh to his
Love, and his Love unto the eyes of his beautious Miſtreſs; inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently
he met within the Hall his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes waiting Gentlewomen with a Viol,
who intreated him to dance with them; and one took his Cloak, and the other his
Sword: Theſe Ladies living rather after the Cuſtom of the <hi>French,</hi>
then the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> did oblige him to gratifie them in their
requeſts. In the mean while <hi>Lozia</hi> asked where her Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomen were;
and one of her Pages told her, that they were dancing with <hi>Clerio.</hi> The
Princeſs being provoked with a deſire to ſee him dance, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded
by the counſels of <hi>Vincia,</hi> ran immediatly to the Hall, and looked
up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <pb n="18" facs="tcp:115129:14"/>him through an hole that was in the Wall ſo long,
till his legs were wearier with leaping, then hers with ſtanding, or her eyes
with beholding ſo pleaſant a proſpect. At laſt ſhe returned to her
Chamber, and began to talk with <hi>Vincia</hi> concerning the gallantneſs
and graceful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of her Couſin, and bid her go down and intreat him to
come up. <hi>Vincia</hi> having given her Couſin the common ſalutation,
took him by the hand, and led him up the ſtairs to the Chamber door of the
Princeſs; at the which he put his Cloak upon his right ſhoulder, and with
his left hand held the hilt of his Sword, and took his Hat in his other hand,
and entered thus into the Chamber with an awful obſervance of the Princeſs,
who riſing a little out of her Chair, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded that they ſhould bring one
for him, and ſet it by her: To whom <hi>Clerio</hi> with a reverend humility
ſaid, Fair Princeſs, I eſteem it a ſuperabundant honour done to me to
ſtand ſo near ſo bright a Sun. The Princeſs ſeeing him of ſo
curteous and noble demeanor, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired <pb n="19" facs="tcp:115129:14"/>him to be pleaſed
to ſit down. I doubt, fair Lady, quoth he, you do but deride me, but ſeeing
you will have it ſo, I cannot ſo far fail in mine obedience to your
Commands as to refuſe it. Then to make it appear how welcom the ſight of
him was, ſhe detained him a long time with her in ſuch diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Sir, is this the faſhion to dreſs your ſelf, as you learned
it in the Court of <hi>France?</hi> methinks it is very comely, and befits you
very well: I perceive the liberty that you Gentlemen have to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel your
ſelves according to your own mind; and thoſe which have moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity
invent the moſt handſom and comely habiliments: You entertain your Ladies
with the moſt honeſt liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and courteous civility that can be
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired; and nothing you have is not at liberty, except ſometimes your
capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated hearts; but yet you are often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſo falſe and unfaithful,
that you may be always juſtly ſuſpected rather to flatter then favour, to
be loved, then to love your Miſtreſſes: Is it poſſible that 
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115129:15"/>you are ſo deeply in love with your Couſin as I am
told?</p>
            <p>Madam, replyed <hi>Clerio,</hi> I do exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly honour and
affect her; but my merit is ſo little, that it is inſufficient to oblige
her ſo much as to render me the like love again. Yes, quoth ſhe, but it is,
even enough for the moſt noble ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits that <hi>Spain</hi> can ſhew,
where there are ſuch whom I do highly honor: But ſpeak the truth, I know
well enough that you are not ſo amorous of <hi>Vincia,</hi> as I have been
made beleeve you are: <hi>Vincia,</hi> what think you of it?</p>
            <p>I beleeve Miſtreſs as you do; he is willing to paſs away his
time, but that he ſhould do it with me, is too much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: I am ſorry for
nothing, but that I am too unworthy to be wedded to ſo worſhipful a
Gentleman; but all the offices of love that I can perform to pleaſure him in
the purſuit of his deſires, I ſhall be ready to adjuvate him with my
beſt aſſiſtance, becauſe of that good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will he doth profeſs he owes
me. <hi>Lozia</hi> taking the words out of <hi>Vincia</hi>'s mouth, 
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115129:15"/>ſaid thus; Moſt Noble <hi>Clerio,</hi> although your
own merits are able Orators to plead your Nobility to any Lady, and diſcover
your excellency to any diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eye; yet if that little I have may be any
ways profitable for you in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining either of your Couſin, or any
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of this Country, make account of my utmoſt endeavors therein, in which
I conceive the courteſie will be not ſo much done to you as to her. And for
my own part, I take ſo much pleaſure in your company, that I wiſh you
ſome honorable Match in this place. I have my ſelf a <hi>French</hi> heart,
although I am a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> woman by Nation: <hi>Vincia</hi> knows how
much I honour any <hi>French</hi> man, eſpecially ſuch who do reſemble
you: Your countenance is a ſure ſign to all that ſee you of thoſe
excellent quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which your ſpirit is endowed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. <hi>Clerio</hi>
was very glad of ſuch an opportunity, whereon he might take hold to praiſe
<hi>Lozia</hi> to her ſelf, and with her true commendations to mingle a
lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of his earneſt and ardent affection.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:115129:16"/>
            <p>Maddam, quoth he, theſe expreſſions of yours, filled with
honour and courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, give me an aſſurance of your excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ingenuity
and courteous diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, together with an evidence to me of mine
unhappineſs by mine eſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from thoſe perfections which you
attribute to me, rather to ſtir up in me a longing after them, then any hope
of the poſſeſſion of them. Nature (to whom you are exceedingly obliged)
hath expreſſed its moſt exquiſite Art in the making of ſo fair a
face, the ſplendor of whoſe beauty doth both aſtoniſh and affect the
hearts of thoſe which are ſo Eagle eyed as to be able to look upon ſo
bright a Sun: And Love it ſelf, as if it were in love with you, hath
beſtowed on you the choiceſt flowers of its Garland to adorn you withall;
Your perfect beauty, your alluring geſtures, that Roſe and Lilly-like
colour mingled together, to beautifie you; Your ſweet behavior and your
courteous carriage are as ſo many inſenſible Spells to charm, or ſweet
ſinging Sirens to entice the nobleſt <pb n="23" facs="tcp:115129:16"/>ſpirits of this
Age to an inevitable amor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Shipwrack. He had proceeded in his diſcourſe,
but was forced abruptly to break of, being interrupted by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in of
ſome Ladies, who caſting their eyes upon him, and ſeeing him ſo
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, began all to load him with Encomiums of Praiſe before
<hi>Lozia,</hi> which added Oyl to the flame of her af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, which had been
before kindled by the ſight of ſo lovely an object. Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which time,
<hi>Clerio</hi> was with his Couſin in a corner of the Chamber, who gave him
an Antidote of Hope againſt his deſpair of ſucceſs. But becauſe
di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt is an inſeparable Concomitant with true love in a Lovers mind,
he could not work this perſwaſion into his heart, that he ſhould ever be
ſo happy as to participate of ſo great a good. The poor Princeſs, during
the preſence of her company, ſat upon thorns, which made her that ſhe
could not ſit ſtill, but muſt needs riſe with one excuſe or other,
that ſhe might look upon her beloved <hi>Clerio;</hi> now and then put a
period to their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, <pb n="24" facs="tcp:115129:17"/>that ſhe might the better
think upon the perſon and the deſerts of him, the thought of whom ſo much
delighted her. In the mean while, Love, which loves not to loſe any time, did
ſo inflame their hearts at one time, that they were no more two, but one.
Noble <hi>Clerio,</hi> what woulſt thou beſtow upon the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger of
ſo welcom news, as ſure as thou think'ſt it uncertain, and thy ſelf
nearer to the poſſeſſion of a dreadful Tomb, then to have occaſion to
triumph in thy victory over thy dear <hi>Lozia? Clerio,</hi> recall thy
ſpirit out of that ſad and dangerous Paroxiſm of affliction wherewith it
is tormented; and whileſt thy Miſtreſs poureth love-tears upon the fire
of thy fervent deſires, devote thy ſelf unto her love, which will make thee
ſo happy by thy love unto her. While <hi>Vincia</hi> was promiſing her
Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin to ſpeak to her Miſtreſs at night in his behalf, one of his
Gentlemen came in to advertiſe him, that an Embaſſador from
<hi>France</hi> was arrived newly, and now at his houſe; and although it was
not uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al <pb n="25" facs="tcp:115129:17"/>for Embaſſadors to lodg in ſuch
hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, yet the quality and merits of <hi>Clerio</hi> made him worthy of
ſo extraordinary a favour. He upon this riſeth preſently, and leſt he
ſhould have been troubleſom to the company, he would have private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
departed. But <hi>Lozia,</hi> whoſe eyes were Gardians for her heart, which
<hi>Clerio</hi> had (without his knowledg) in poſſeſſion, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
acquainted her with his departure. Whereupon, filled with love, yet with wary
diſcretion, ſhe roſe up, and ſaid to him in a courteous manner, Noble
Sir, what is the cauſe you will ſo ſoon for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake our company? To whom
he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated the reaſon of his departing, and then after a complemental
farewel did go home to his houſe, which was direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppoſite to his
Miſtreſſes, and welcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Embaſſador with kind entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
After they had diſcourſed a little while of ſerious affairs, he took his
Lute, and ſet himſelf down at the window, playing moſt melodiouſly
thereupon: <hi>Lozia</hi> hearing this excellent Harmony, went to hear it at
the window, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired <pb n="26" facs="tcp:115129:18"/>the Gentlewomen to come and
participate of her pleaſure, whoſe ears he contented no leſs by the
melody of his Muſick, then their eyes by the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his countenance.
Theſe Ladies a little after took their leaves of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, who
returned them thanks for their kindneſs, and then retired into her Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet,
to give audie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to thoſe importunate love-thoughts that preſſed ſo
hard upon her heart, which new gueſts ſpoke after this ſort; It is our
common cuſtom to go viſit all thoſe Ladies which have ſubmitted
themſelves to our Empire, that giving our ſelves into their
poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we may get their Souls by way of retaliation into our
power.</p>
            <p>My friends (quoth <hi>Lozia</hi>) I know not how I can with love
refuſe you, and much leſs how with ſafety I can receive you, a thouſand
things prohibit me the firſt, and my paſſion onely councels me to the
ſecond, but in vain do I enter the liſts of diſpute with you, who have
al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready deſprived me inſenſibly of the uſe of my Reaſon, and with a
dolorous <pb n="27" facs="tcp:115129:18"/>ſigh and a doleful voyce which were evident
ſymptomes of an afflicted ſpirit, ſhe breathed out this ſubſequent
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            <p>O delightfull liberty! which hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to I have ſtedfaſtly
preſerved from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thraldome, to ſo many puiſſant Princes who have
uſed their utmoſt power to captivate it to their love and merits. A liberty
no more a liberty, but a ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſlave unto a thouſand fooliſh
paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: to thee I profeſs I am exceedingly obliged for keeping me ſo
long a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander over the moſt noble Spirits of this age, whom I have
tirannically wounded. And thou ô divine Reaſon! now I come to take my
farewell of thee permit me to give thee thy laſt em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces, and that having
been ſo famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arly conjoyned, I ſhould now ſhed ſome tears of ſorrow
for ſo long and irk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome a ſeparation: Farewell.</p>
            <p>But Reaſon interrupted her farther Soliloquies: ſaying,</p>
            <p>Fair Princeſs, what is it that thus you perplex your ſelf
about? intend you to <pb n="28" facs="tcp:115129:19"/>ruinate that honour and renown, which
hath ſo long a time run in the veines of your predeceſſors? conſider
that if you wholly devote your ſelf, being yet but a child, to the government
of your unbridled paſſions, you will become one of the meaneſt ſhrubs
that hath grown in ſo great a garden; you will take the crown of glory off
your head and lay it in the duſt, and then no doubt if it be quickly buried
by the tomb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of reproach, you will ſpoyle the glorious garland of your
honour by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the choyſeſt flower away to ſo mean a perſon, and
darken your glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sun by conjunction with ſo ſmall a ſtar; what if
the wound in your repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, ſhould not be utterly incureable, yet at
leaſt your credit wil be accounted little, in the worlds valuation, by
reaſon of the remainder of the ſcar? Cannot you who are a peerleſs
Princeſs both in goods and goodneſs, elect ſome mighty Monarch, and in
ſtead of a baſe degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration by your fooliſh love into a lower ſtock,
aſcend by a lawful and honorable <pb n="29" facs="tcp:115129:19"/>marriage, into a more
noble family? Shall not you have more contentment in the being a mother unto a
Noble Prince, who will carry upon his front the lively image both of your
mighty husband and your ſelf, which will give cauſe of hope and expectation
to your ſervants, who will be much lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of his friends, and more feared of
his Foes, then to be matched unto a low not to ſay vile perſon, who will be
equally ſlighted by your friends and ſcorned by your enemies? The charm
muſt needs be very great which hath thrown all your ſenſes into ſuch a
ſwoon, that they are inſenſible of their pains, and foreſee not their
inevitable perdition, 'tis neither the ſlight account that you make of me,
nor the fear of my unhappineſs, which doth provoke me to ſuch complaints,
but rather a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable ſympathizing with you in your unavoideable miſery,
for whilſt I ſee you ſuch an exile from your ſelf, torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with
ſuch ſtinging griefs, I can do no leſs, but do this my laſt Office as
the <pb n="30" facs="tcp:115129:20"/>ſafeſt remedie to recall your Spirit from out of
that mortall dream of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull conceits, upon which you rumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and raife
you from the thoughts of fooliſh fancies, to ſettle your affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon
more honourable objects.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lozia</hi> knew her fault but knew not where to finde a
remedie to amend it, full both with love and with grief ſhe vented out
theſe ſayings. My loving friend theſe worthy and weightie coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels would
be ſufficient to turn me from fome light and little love, but not from ſo
paſſionate affection which hath already gained ſo abſolute a conqueſt
over me, that I account all imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments whatſoever as unprofitable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
thoſe which give me occaſions and oppertunities to meditate upon ſo
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fireable a ſubject. Thou propoſeſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to me but vanitie, glorie,
ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and oftentation, which are lent out but for uſe and taken away in
an inſtant leaving nothing behind but a ſting of ſorrow, becauſe they
cannot be regained. This life is ſo ſhort yet ſo fil'd with 
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115129:20"/>thorns that they are miſerable indeed who to fill their
cheſts with gold and their perſons with praiſe, empty their eyes of
reſt, and their ſpirits of ſweet contentment, fill their heads with
ſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cares to get, and their hearts with fears to loſe what may be
ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. It is a great default in fathers duty, to ſeek for ſuch
marriages for their children, where there is a great ſtock of money, but none
of love, wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them rather to the portion then the perſon, and not give
them liberty to choſe where they like and ſettle their loves upon worthy,
though not wealthy perſons: ſatisfaction riſeth not out of
ſuperfluitie, neither diſcontent from want. I can be well contented with an
empty purſe together with the full en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of my beloved <hi>Clerio,</hi>
and had rather be a ſervant unto him, then the Queen of the moſt
flouriſhing King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in the world; rather had I be a ſubject to him then
have the world ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject unto me. What are Dukedomes and ſuch things to me,
which can neither <pb n="32" facs="tcp:115129:21"/>ſatiate my deſires nor content my
ſpirit; my <hi>Clerio,</hi> his deſerts will be a ſufficient dowry, to
which I will add ſome chains of precious Margarites and peeces of pure gold,
which will maintain my love and I in any part of the world, in which we will
live as Princes, though not Princes over it. It is an act of a weak judgment
not to content it ſelf with leſs then the ſurpluſage of what it hath,
which ſhould be willingly ſpared in the time of adverſitie, but uſed at
pleaſure for contentations only in the calm of proſperity. Had not I better
voluntarily deprive my ſelf of the poſſeſſion of a Principality more
abſolutely to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the Virtues of <hi>Clerio,</hi> then keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the
poſſeſſion of mine eſtate, ſhould by a bloody War be ſhamefully
driven out of all, as <hi>Craeſus</hi> was by <hi>Cyrus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This poor Princeſs was ſo enamored with <hi>Clerio,</hi> that
doubting of her ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesfull iſſue, ſhe reſolved rather to loſe her
eſtate then her ſervant; more would ſhe have ſaid to <hi>Vincia,</hi>
had not one come to call her to Supper. The <pb n="33" facs="tcp:115129:21"/>Princeſs
hearing the voyce of her Lady of Honour, framed her countenance as well as
ſhe could to its wonted colour, leſt ſhe ſhould perceive it change,
ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing that <hi>Clerio</hi> was in love with <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> which
might be a <hi>remora</hi> to her pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous proceedings. But ſhe did it
not ſo cunningly, but <hi>Vincia</hi> read in her face what grieved her
heart; as diſſembling goes not long undiſcovered before a diſcerning
eye, and frequent familiarity advantaged likewiſe her knowledg of the change
of her Soul by that alteration that appeared in her face.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vincia</hi> very joyful that her affairs did go forward
without any impediment, did not as yet make any ſhew of her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to her
Miſtreſs for fear of diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing her: but ſeeing her
diſquietneſs was likely to continue, not being as a Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flood for the
preſent ſwelling over the banks, but a conſtant ſpring, which would
never ceaſe to caſt out its water, till it were dryed up by the enjoyment
of her long'd for <hi>Clerio:</hi> She, as curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to know her diſtemper,
and cautious <pb n="34" facs="tcp:115129:22"/>of her health, would demand the cauſe of
ſuch a ſudden change. All ſupper time ſhe did ſo narrowly eye her
acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that ſhe was paſt all peradventure perſwaded that ſhe was in
a love-ſick Paroxiſm. Then began the Princeſs to revive her ſpirit with
the exhilerating thoughts of excellent <hi>Clerio;</hi> then again is there
ingendred in her breſt carneſt deſires for his ſweet enjoyments, with
affectionate ſighings for that long'd for opportunity, whoſe lives were no
ſooner began by love, but they were ſtrangled in the womb by fear and
diſcretion: Her humid eyes firmly faſtened downward, her trembling body,
her unaccuſtomed ſtartlings and diſquietneſs, her asking for one thing
in ſtead of another, would have ſufficiently evidenced her perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity of
ſpirit to any body, which would have added the leaſt ſuſpicion to an
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent mind. As ſoon as <hi>Vincia</hi> was gone from table, ſhe
wrote this Letter unto her Couſin.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>CLERIO, Your merits and your win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing behavior are ſuch
powerful Orators for <pb n="35" facs="tcp:115129:22"/>you to your Miſtreſs, that I hope
you will not need your Couſins help: I have many things to acquaint you
withall, but thoſe I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpeak then write, thereby to be honored
with your company; I fear this unexpected joy may be as great an impediment to
your reſt, as your accuſtomed afflictions were.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Clerio</hi> read the Letter, but did not make an appearance of
any change, leſt <hi>Lozia</hi>'s Page ſhould diſcover any thing thereby.
After he had prayed him to ſtay till he returned, he went into his Cloſet,
and wrote this enſuing An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>I ſhould, did not I repoſe my whole confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in your
gracious endeavors, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor my hopes upon the aſſurance of your
conſtancy, be toſſed up and down, as a Ship is upon the waves, in the
expectation of ſo great a happineſs as you promiſe to me; and if many
others had not received the like courteſies and favours from Fortune as I now
do wait for, I ſhould doubt of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of my deſires: I have
deſired nothing more then the fruition of the fair <hi>Lozia,</hi> as
witneſſeth my ſuperlative paſsions to be <pb n="36" facs="tcp:115129:23"/>her
ſervant, which I have much deſired, but yet have deſpaired hitherto to
encompaſs, becauſe ſhe is the moſt fair and famous Princeſs in the
world.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Lozia</hi> ſuſtaining her ſpirit with hope to finiſh
her begun love, would often turn her eyes towards the Chamber of her ſervant,
upon what errand you know well enough; but miſſing the view of
<hi>Clerio,</hi> ſhe ſaw her Page with a Letter in his hand coming from his
houſe, to whom ſhe preſently ſent one of her Gentlewomen for the Letter
and the Page before he had ſpoken to any body: Preſently the Gentlewoman
went and conducted the Page unto <hi>Lozia,</hi> who was alone in a Gallery.
<hi>Lozia</hi> demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed who had ſent him to <hi>Clerio</hi> his houſe; he
not knowing any thing, freely told her, that <hi>Vincia</hi> had ſent him
with a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to her Couſin, and he had there the Anſwer to it. She
without any more ado opened the Letter, and read it, and not dreaming of any
thing leſs then the ardent affections that were in <hi>Clerio</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
her, at the ſight of ſuch unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected <pb n="37" facs="tcp:115129:23"/>tydings ſhe was
raviſhed almoſt between love and the extaſie of joy: Wherefore ſhe
commanded the Page to go his way, that he might not diſcover that ſudden
and cheerful alteration that was eaſily legible in her countenance. Who hath
ſeen the Sun after he hath for a ſeaſon retired from us, return, and with
his glittering beams diſſipate all thoſe miſts, clouds and vapors that
did ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure our light, and with a fair day give us alſo ſo fructifying a
warmth, that the Earth which did before in his abſence bring forth nothing
but brambles and thiſtles, by the profitable approach thereof is made the
mother of a fruitful Harveſt; he might have alſo ſeen the Sun of his Love
diſperſe thoſe griefs and ſorrows, and diſcloud thoſe gloomy days,
and enliven a number of ſweet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights and joyful raptures, which before
were ſtifled with immoderate fears. This fair Princeſs, after ſhe had
read and kiſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Letter an hundred and an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred times, uttered forth
theſe words, drawn from the bottom of her affected heart:</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:115129:24"/>
            <p>If thoſe Mortals are eſteemed moſt happy, and moſt in
Heavens favor, which are moſt gratified with divine Benedic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, there is
no Princeſs in the world which at this time can truly ſay ſhe is more
happy then my ſelf, who am ſo highly honored by the moſt perfect and
peerleſs Gentleman in all the world, whoſe vertues and perſon I
reverence, admire and adore altogether as much as the love and knowledg that I
already have of his unmatchable merits do ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige me. O ſweet Letter, I
cannot but kiſs thee once again, ſeeing thou haſt been touched with the
hands of my <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio;</hi> let me behold thee with admiration and affection,
ſeeing I find in thee ſo perfect pleaſure; let me read thee, that I might
retain in memory thoſe ſelected words of thine, which aſſure me of thy
love, my noble <hi>Clerio.</hi> O mine head, open the flood-gates of thy tears,
and expend them upon the exceſs of thy preſent extaſie of joy. O mine
heart, ſtill contribute more fuel unto the flames of thine affections, and
make as <pb n="39" facs="tcp:115129:24"/>it were a bonefire therein, in token of triumph for
thy conqueſt over ſo loving an enemy. <hi>Lozia</hi> being a little
recovered from this ſweet and ſudden tranſporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, call'd
<hi>Vincia,</hi> and took her by the hand, and told her her heart, ſaying,
You know the affection which I have born to you ever ſince you entered into
my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and thoſe deſires I have had to do you any courteſie; but
your not having occaſion, nor I opportunity to oblige you, muſt not be
objected againſt my natural diſpoſition, which inclineth me to engage
indifferently all ſorts of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but principally thoſe to whom I am
deeply indebted, as I am to you: And if the ſenſibility of ſo many
faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſervices which I have received from you, ſhould not draw me to an
acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of your affections; yet mine own honour and reputation and your
deſerts would freely force me to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure your advancement. I know that you
having a ſufficient eſtate, have made choyce of me among many others, who
have deſired you not for any inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niency <pb n="40" facs="tcp:115129:25"/>in your
affairs, but affection unto my welfare: I am not ignorant of your quality, nor
thoſe perfections where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you are endowed, which is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon I have
permitted you ſo familiar a ſociety with my ſelf above all others which
are near me: There is not need of any other teſtimony of the truth thereof,
then your own knowledg: But if it fall out to my misfortune, to have more need
of your aſſiſtance then you have of my protection, will you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<hi>Vincia</hi> ceaſe to continue your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer favours, (and upon the
utterance of theſe words embraced her, and poured from her beautiful eyes a
pearly ſhowre of tears upon the boſom of <hi>Vincia,</hi>) and eſpecially
in one thing wherein I am conſtrained to come to you for counſel, and to
bind you by the ſtricteſt Oaths that can be made to ſpeak the truth? Is
it true that <hi>Clerio</hi> is ſo deeply drowned with ſorrow, and ſo
fervent and paſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate for the love he bears me, as appears by the Letter
he hath wrote to you, which I have ſubtilly gotten from the 
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115129:25"/>Page which carried him yours?</p>
            <p>Madam, ſaid <hi>Vincia,</hi> I conceive none ſhould ever
diſſemble before Princes, and conceal any thing that they ſhould
diſcover, much leſs ſhould I to you, to whom I am a ſervant as well as
ſubject. The truth is, this <hi>Clerio</hi> hath for ſix Moneths been
exceedingly amorous of you, and hath not acquainted me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, till within
this day or two: Your Greatneſs cauſed in me as great appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of
his misfortune, as did his vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent paſſion pity in me for his pains: But
ſeeing that his good fortune hath grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him ſo much honour from you, as
to prevent the extream deſires he hath for you, with the ineſtimable good
of your favour; My Miſtreſs, I proſtrate my ſelf at your feet, humbly
to adore you for the honour you beſtow upon us, proteſting to you, that
ſeeing you judg us worthy of it, we will return you as much obedience and
humble ſervice, as (if I durſt ſay it) that you ſhall be more happy in
the mean condition of your <hi>Clerio,</hi> who will all his life long 
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115129:26"/>believe that his <hi>Summum Bonum</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth upon your
gracious aſpects, then if you had made a more ambitious election. This noble
Princeſs, impatient to ſee her at her feet, interrupted her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe
in the middle, to raiſe her up, and embracing of her, ſaid;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vincia,</hi> my dear Couſin, it is not me to whom you give
this duty, a poſture inconſiſtent with mine honour to tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate; but from
henceforth ought you to live with me, as the moſt kind and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nign Couſin
that you have in the world. I ſo much honor the merits both of you and your
Couſin <hi>Clerio,</hi> that I will prefer any one that belongeth to him
before the neareſt relations I have. Let us forget all thoſe paſſed
vanities full of pricking thorns, the Roſes whereof are gathered by frequent
familiarity. I perceive my ſelf to be ſo perfectly happy by the love of you
and your Couſin, that I deſire we may conſult of a way to conceal it from
the watchful eyes of ſo many that ſpy after my actions; I know your
ſpirit is able to find out ſome fit invention.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:115129:26"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Vincia</hi> anſwered her, Miſtreſs it is very late and I
am afraid that you may get ſome ſickneſs, or at leaſt your folks which
are ſo ſuſpicious may doubt ſomething to ſee us talk ſo long
toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. I pray Miſtreſs go to bed, for this buſineſs deſerveth to
be dreamt of a little: to morrow <hi>Clerio</hi> ſhall come ſee you, who
being of a very quick appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, and advantaged by the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his
exceeding happineſs in your favour, will ſoon finde out a way to continue
us all in ſo happy a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lozia,</hi> approving her counſel, went to bed preſently,
and when her gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women were withdrawn, and ſhe alone with <hi>Vincia,</hi>
ſhe began to delight her ſelf with the imagination of her new lover: after
ſome love talk <hi>Vincia</hi> asked her if ſhe wiſhed <hi>Clerio</hi>
was there, ſhe anſwered her ſmilingly, Yes <hi>Vincia,</hi> provided you
are there: and what, you would be afraid of him? No, but I ſhould be
aſham'd. <hi>Vincia</hi> ſeeing the childiſhneſs of this child, began
to <pb n="44" facs="tcp:115129:27"/>laugh, and begged of her to ſleep; ſleep had ho
ſooner with the night of her eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lids obſcured thoſe two fair Suns, her
eyes, but a pleaſant dream crept into her head, and lodged there till the
morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Her Soul, half raviſhed with theſe ſweet delights, had
continued longer in this amorous extaſie, had not <hi>Vincia</hi> call'd her
out of it: Her eyes at their opening, as a clear and ruddy morning, gave light
to a thouſand beauties and graces that Heaven and Nature had with their own
hands made appear upon her face: Her gently languag'd mouth, enriched with a
red Coral, open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it ſelf to diſcloſe the dream to <hi>Vincia,</hi> and
perfuming with her odoriferous breath all the air of the chamber at the ſame
time, diſcovers in her mouth the richeſt and moſt Orient Pearls and
Treaſures that the Eaſt can ſhew, which would equally enamor and
aſtoniſh all that ſaw it. This fair Princeſs began thus:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vincia,</hi> thou haſt done me a diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to
deprive me of thoſe ſweet enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <pb n="45" facs="tcp:115129:27"/>my ſleep
afforded me; and that thou mayſt give me thine advice con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſuch
wonderful things, I will recount them to thee as well as I can.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vincia,</hi> I was no ſooner aſleep, but methoughts I was
in a great Forreſt of Cedars and Palm-trees, where there was the moſt
delightfulleſt Walks that can be deſired; the warbling noiſe of a
thouſand Nightingales did make it ſo ſweetly reſound, that a Lute,
whoſe ſtrings are dextrouſly fingered by ſome experienced Nymph, could
not make ſuch pleaſant Harmony: Conſtantly keeping in the midſt of
theſe delights, at laſt I met with an Hermit, who came thither to gather
Herbs and Roots for his refection, according to his cuſtom, for forty Years.
This good father, after he had courteouſly ſaluted me, accoaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me, and
asked me if I deſired to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thoſe moſt remarkable things that were
near his Cave; beleeve, Curioſity had conſtrained me to go walk there, and
ſetting himſelf before, prayed me to <pb n="46" facs="tcp:115129:28"/>follow him: we had
not gone two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred paces, but at the end of the Wood we met with one of the
faireſt Dens that could poſſibly be made, built by two Lovers, ſo
ſumptuouſly in ſweet ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs to enjoy their amorous deſires:
Entering within the door, we ſaw two white Torches lighted, that the Souls of
theſe two Lovers carried in their hands, the better to guide all thoſe that
came thither: At the entry there was a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, enriched with all ſorts of
workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip that either Art or Nature could af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford it; <hi>Venus</hi>
pourtrayed in white Marble, excellently imboſſed, with a thouſand hearts
under her feet, as a Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy of her Beauty, and in her hand ſhe had a cup of
Agate, out of which ſhe poureth pure water to waſh the hands of thoſe
which do come in. Paſſing fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, theſe Torches lighting us, we came
into the Cave it ſelf, at the entrance whereof was another great Fountain,
fifteen paces ſquare, covered all over with pure Marble, in which by an
incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible Art was made ſwim an Hart, a <pb n="47" facs="tcp:115129:28"/>couple of Dogs,
and two Hunters fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing them, all of Marble, into which this water did
pleaſantly inſpire motion and voyce; on each ſide was a delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
Forreſt in boſs, of Marble too, filled with Birds ſo livelily painted,
that they would have been taken for living, whoſe melodious ſinging was
ſo ſweet, that Art excelled Nature it ſelf: A thouſand Characters,
Trophies of Love and Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, were read of theſe faithful Lovers, written
with their own hands, and indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by their paſſions, upon the Pillar and
all the angles of this ſpacious Cave: Six Nymphs did ſing ſo pleaſantly
in honor of their love, that it is hard to ſay whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there were more
pleaſure to the ears in the hearing of their voyce, or to the eyes in the
beholding of ſo compleat and perfect beauty that they were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned with.
<hi>Vincia,</hi> I ſhould never have been weary of theſe delicious
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, if the Hermit had not taken me away to ſhew me a fair River
covered with Swans, and the ſides adorned with rows of precious Stones, which
ſerved <pb n="48" facs="tcp:115129:29"/>for Walks to theſe two Lovers, and for a
ſubject to help them to diſcourſe of their paſſionate diſtempers.
Delighting my ſelf with the pleaſure which I could not but have in ſo
delightful a place, I ſaw before me a Peacock, who went from us as faſt as
we advanced towards him, and made a famous ſhew with his fair Feathers, which
did reſemble ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Suns; I never ſaw ſo beautious an one in all my
life: and juſt then you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakened me. <hi>Vincia,</hi> I deſire you to
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to me your opinion concerning this Dream.</p>
            <p>Madam, I am not quickſighted enough to ſee the bottom of this
Dream, nor a capable Interpreter of ſo obſcure a Rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, which promiſeth
you according to my apprehenſion a world of content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and good Fortune:
But there is in this Town a moſt eminent <hi>Magician,</hi> to whom if you
pleaſe to do this honour as to ſend to know, he will be very glad to tell
you his utmoſt knowledg. <hi>Vincia</hi> judged according to her capacity
that this was a true Hierogliphick of the love <pb n="49" facs="tcp:115129:29"/>of
<hi>Lozia,</hi> which ſhould ſucceed to the advantage of her Couſin; and
therefore to give more weight and credit to the Interpretation, had rather
another ſhould unfold it, who was altogether unconcerned in the buſineſs,
and leſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to <hi>Clerio</hi> then ſhe was, whoſe affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and
affection might have been weighty cauſes of the queſtioning of the truth of
her words. With this honeſt excuſe ſhe ſatisfied <hi>Lozia,</hi>
whoſe curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity yet unſatisfied ſent to fetch him: As ſoon as he had
ſpoken with the Page, and deſired him to ſtay a little for him, he went
into his chamber, and falls to his Invocation, Spells, Charms, and all other
ſorts of Tricks, that he might be inſtructed of his Devils of what
<hi>Lozia</hi> would ask him, unwilling to preſent him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf before ſo
great a Princeſs like an <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noramus,</hi> without ability to reſolve
her demands, or elſe to terrifie her with the appearance of his Circles,
Spirits, &amp;c. With this wiſe foreſight he went to <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zia,</hi> who
did with <hi>Vincia</hi> ſtay for him in a Cloſet: As ſoon as he came
they ſhut <pb n="50" facs="tcp:115129:30"/>the door, and <hi>Lozia</hi> declared her Dream
to him, with deſires to be reſolved of the truth of it as near as he could,
telling him ſhe ſent for him not to flatter her, but befriend her with the
true declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the conſequents of her Dream; and though ſhe was never
ſo great, yet ſhe was as ſubject to the ſiniſter acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, as
gracious aſpects of Fortune; and that if Nature and Heaven had in her
minority made her partaker of the goods and glory of the world, and ſet her
upon the pinacle of preferment, yet was it likewiſe powerful and puiſſant
e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to throw her down into the ditch of diſgrace, and make her as
wretched as ſhe hath been happy. The Magician ſeeing the liberty he had
allowed him, ſaid;</p>
            <p>Madam, The commandment by which you do oblige me to ſpeak
freely, doth ſo well agree with my deſires and my profeſſion, that I am
very glad to ſee my ſelf out of the fears I had you would not delight
therein: my words ſhall not conſtrain you to any thing in the world, 
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:115129:30"/>but leave you to your free conſent, and only explicate
and unfold the words and meaning of your Dream. The Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven which ſuiteth
with your inclination to lead you inſenſibly to your deſtiny, may (as the
author of the cauſe) change alſo the effect and event of your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,
which I judg to be very uneven, now elevated, then dejected. This For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
and Gave preſage to you a pleaſura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſolitary life. This Hermit
fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheweth one which will ſerve you as a Guide and great Agitator in your
af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs. The Dogs and Hunters which chaſe this Hart is your good, which your
kinsfolk and enemies will purſue to the end. The chirping Birds, the
Characters, the Songs and the Nymphs, are but ſo many ſweet delights and
contentments which you ſhall enjoy. Thoſe pleaſant Walks for the Lovers
alone, who almoſt only live free from glory, ambition and jealouſie, among
the flowers, and the full enjoyment, not of goods, but ſweet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment,
and an hundred amorous ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhments which this green place doth 
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:115129:31"/>promiſe, accommodating it ſelf not only to the eyes,
but to the delights of the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Souls of the Lovers; each moment new
occaſions will occaſion freſh joy and delights. This Peacock is the
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon you affect, who although he be a Gentleman, yet notwithſtanding
ſhall be as far from your Greatneſs, as the feet of the Peacock diſagree
with his feathers; but thoſe fair Suns that he ſeemed to carry, are his
excellent endowments, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and perfections which ſhall inflame your ſoul
with an amorous heat; that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering him before a thouſand others, you
ſhall become after your clandeſtine love ſo famous by his courage, that
you ſhall judg your ſelf happy in his marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age: But this River covered
with Swans denoteth a change of Fortune, which ſhall carry you a great way,
and as the Swans dye when the ſweetneſs of their ſinging is moſt
delectable, ſo after an infinite number of happy days, you will dye with that
in your arms which you love moſt in the world, when you ſhall be beſt
contented, and ſwimming in the <pb n="53" facs="tcp:115129:31"/>midſt of the River of
peace, proſperity and delights. Although <hi>Lozta</hi> was but young, yet
ſhe was Miſtreſs in the art of diſſimulation, making as if ſhe
regarded not theſe ſo deſirable news, fearing leſt the Magician
ſhould diſcover any thing of her intentions, which might be an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment
to her love, which were repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the life by the unfolding of this
Dream, the true Prophecy of her Deſtiny, and with a countenance as pale as
her heart was hot with the flames of love, ſhe ſaid,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mounſier,</hi> I cannot without wronging both mine own
judgment and your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts, doubt of your ſufficiency, which all the world
admireth not as a man, but rather as the Oracle of this Age; yet cannot I
believe that love can make me ſo far forget my duty as to love a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman,
ſeeing I cannot ſufficiently e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem ſuch who, equalling my birth and
means, honour me ſo far as to love me: But I doubt not but my cruel Fortune
may take ſome other way to ruine me, then by running away with ſuch a
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <pb n="54" facs="tcp:115129:32"/>and ſo this way your Prophetick words will
agree with my adverſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: But though it ſhould be ſo, yet I pray
you ſay nothing thereof, becauſe the people repoſing ſuch confidence in
your words, will hold them for true di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinations of my future misfortune; and
further, the publique fame thereof will be as diſadvantageous as
diſpleaſing to to me, whoſe miſery will come ſoon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough without the
addition of wings. And then putting her hand into her poc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, ſhe drew out a
purſe with two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Crowns, which ſhe prepared for him; and when ſhe
had put it into his hands, to whom he ſaid, the reſidue of his help was at
her ſervice, when op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity ſhould afford him means to effect it, and
whatſoever happened to <hi>Lozia</hi> to make her unhappy, yet her whole life
ſhould be exceeding content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; though Fortune took away the firſt as his,
yet Vertue did preſerve the other. In this inſtant <hi>Vincin</hi> heard
ſome one tread in the Gallery, which made them all ſilent to hear who it
was; <hi>Vincia</hi> 
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:115129:32"/>told her it was the Duke of
<hi>Blanfort</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Doudonne: Lozia</hi> run preſently to
meet them, and <hi>Vincia</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed the Magician out another way, and came
inſtantly to her Miſtreſs to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company her. The Duke of
<hi>Blanfort</hi> meeting her, ſaluted her, who was yet undreſſed
almoſt at dinner time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mounſier,</hi> quoth <hi>Lozia,</hi> you will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count me
very lazy to be yet undreſſed, but the reaſon is, becauſe I have been
buſied all the morning in looking upon the thing in my Cabinet; but if it
pleaſe you to dine here, I will be ready by that time you have walked two or
three turns in the Garden. I am willing, my Niece. And after he had took his
leave of her, he went down: <hi>Lozia</hi> gave him <hi>Vincia</hi> to
diſcourſe with till ſhe was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and took one of her Gentlewomen to
help her attire her ſelf. The Prince of <hi>Doudonne,</hi> her Couſin and
ſervant ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with her, who would one while hold the Looking-glaſs,
then would give her a Ribbon, thinking by ſuch amorous ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices to render
himſelf more acceptable <pb n="56" facs="tcp:115129:33"/>to <hi>Lozia,</hi> hoping that
ſhe in concluſion would affect him not as a loving Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin, but a
paſſionate Miſtreſs. But poor Lovers, how do I bemoan you, who, forced
either by deſtiny or inclination, do deſperately affect your Miſtreſs,
who do publiquely honour you, when in their Souls they diſeſteem and
contemn you as ſordid ſervants; they ſweetly ſhew the Roſes and
Lillies in their hands and and faces (though far from their hearts) to thoſe
that do reſpect them, and ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give the Thorns to thoſe that ſerve
them, that after a thouſand griefs and wounds and ſorrows they may make
your patiences condign with ſuch paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and that your blood may
ſerve for a ſacrifice to their parts and graces, which conquer the
greateſt Conquerors, and captivate them to their pleaſure, who have
undergone the greateſt perils. They have eyes full of ſweet alluring
glances and charms to ſubjugate the moſt famous ſpirits, whoſe hope
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth not upon your deſerts, but on their ſickle humors. This is that
in which <pb n="57" facs="tcp:115129:33"/>the condition of Lovers is miſerable: For he is
more happy which meeteth with his Miſtreſſes inclination, then he which
is filled both with grace and goodneſs. Poor blind people, you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of the
diſcretion, not the love, that forceth them to tender you this duty: You are
poſſeſſed with a folly next to madneſs, to imagine, that this Sex,
which is the weaker, hath more Reaſon and Judgment then you which ordinarily
honour ill-favored and fooliſh perſons, and paſs by both amiable and
honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Objects. Do not you think, that they are often troubled with
fantaſtical humors, which carry them beyond the bounds of Reaſon, and even
the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the condition and deſerts of thoſe who deſire to ſerve
them, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their own fancies, in the loving and eſteeming thoſe who
are unworthy, and ſlighting of thoſe which are deſerving? If they are
indifferent fair and rich, a thouſand folks as well as you will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor to
acquire their good grace, and this cannot be without a thouſand un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet 
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:115129:34"/>and vexing thoughts: If they are already engaged, you may
as ſoon ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due a Kingdom as conquer them, and well leave your deſigns to
Courtiers, who knowing not where to imploy their time better then in familiar
frequenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Ladies companies (which is the laſt and the beſt file to
poliſh the nobleſt ſpirits) may at their leaſure and pleaſure
ſtretch out theſe amorous ſtrings to their own contentment, and
ſuſtain all defeats and denyals with incredible pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience. I ſpeak to
thoſe which ſerve La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, as the Prince of <hi>Doudonne</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
others did the Princeſs <hi>Lozia</hi> to gain her love, and were all
repulſed to aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the honour of a Gentleman, who was raiſed upon their
rejections, and ſerved himſelf with their diſdain as a Trophy, to honour
his triumph for his conqueſt over the beauty and graces of his Miſtreſs,
who as ſoon as ſhe was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coutred, not according to her cuſtom, but her
haſte, with a white Damask Gown lined with Sattin, and a Peticoat of Silver
Cloth, and ſo went down to <pb n="59" facs="tcp:115129:34"/>her Uncle, who was
diſcourſing to <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia</hi> concerning the deſign he had to wed his
daughter to her Miſtreſs, and intreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her to aſſiſt him therein,
knowing how prevalent ſhe was with her; he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed her money, means,
love, affections, profit, pleaſure, and what not? and would have perſued
his diſcourſe, but that the ſweet voyce of his Neice did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt him.
This unparallel'd Princeſs in beauty and grace did with a ſmiling face
deſire the Duke of <hi>Blanfort</hi> to go to dinner, and excuſed her
ſelf for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him ſtay ſo long. Her Uncle did find her ſo courteous,
that he ſaid, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath made you ſo amiable and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly beauteous,
that I find you more gracefully arrayed with your graces and beauties, then any
other can be with the moſt rich Stuffs and Orient Pearls of the Eaſt: I
wonder not if your merits and beauty do acquire ſo many gallant ſervants,
and if the knowledg you have thereof maketh you ſo diſdainfully han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle
them; and I proteſt you have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for it; for I conceive that the moſt
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:115129:35"/>meritorious Prince in <hi>Europe</hi> cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
your honorable grace, unleſs that doth more voluntarily reſign it ſelf,
then any ways merit it.</p>
            <p>Sir, quoth the lovely <hi>Lozia,</hi> you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin dinner with
deriding me, and ſpare me no more then ſtrangers: I do poſſeſs
theſe deſerts and beauties rather from your gallant application, then from
the gift of Nature, for which I have more cauſe to complain, then I am
beholding to your complement, which hath attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted that unto me which Nature
hath denyed me: I do beleeve my portion rather then my perſon, and my means
then my merits, do oblige ſo many to honour me with their love, who
ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time praiſing and commending me for the defects in my Soul and my
parts, which rather provoke me to bewail my miſery, then fooliſhly affect
their hiper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical expreſſions: And if I ſhould be ſo beautiful as
they would make me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, the apprehenſion of the loſs of that little I
have, moveth me with as much diſpleaſure, as the poſſeſſion can
give me <pb n="61" facs="tcp:115129:35"/>content. Seeing the Table covered, they altered
their diſcourſe, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving from a Gentleman her ſervant a Towel,
offered the end thereof to her Uncle, who refuſed to waſh firſt, and
therefore both did together; and after they had a little diſputed about the
ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norableſt place of the Table, he with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaties and the command he had
over her forced her to take it, as it did belong to her; for <hi>Lozia</hi> was
an hundred times more honorable then he, who but a yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger brother, his mother
was but mean, but his greatneſs proceeded from his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſide, who was a
Prince of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Blood of <hi>Spain,</hi> who took his wife for her
pulchritude and perfections; and though ſhe was a Princeſs, yet not of half
ſo Noble Blood: therefore the Duke of <hi>Blanfort</hi> knew well enough what
he denyed to his Niece. During dinner, <hi>Lozia,</hi> that ſhe might fall in
talk of her <hi>Clerio,</hi> began to ſpeak to <hi>Vincia</hi> of her Suitor,
who, fitted for her humor, anſwered her according to hearts deſire, which
ſhe did on purpoſe to remove all <pb n="62" facs="tcp:115129:36"/>jealouſies and
ſuſpicion of the frequent viſitations of <hi>Clerio.</hi> The Duke of
<hi>Blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi> not knowing him, was very curious to know who it was:
<hi>Lozia</hi> told him he ſhould ſee him after dinner, he will have a care
not to fail; he requires more courteſies of me then I can beſtow upon him
in order to his love, I wiſh he would wed her, for he is an honeſt
Gentleman; but what ſhould I do if I loſe <hi>Vincia?</hi> I had rather he
were dead. And then addreſſing her ſelf to <hi>Vincia,</hi> asked, Do you
indeed love him very heartily? I do affect him as my Couſin, anſwered
<hi>Vincia,</hi> and honour him as a Gentleman of ſo much merit as you ſee
in him. Upon this there came in two Ladies to deſire the Princeſs to come
to the nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials of one of the faireſt Virgins in all the Town, where there
was a Dance, and divers young folk to run the Ring. The Princeſs, who knew
her, and was willing to paſs away the afternoon in ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation,
promiſed them to go thither as ſoon as ſhe could after dinner. The
La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies went away very well contented, as <pb n="63" facs="tcp:115129:36"/>aſſured of
the preſence of the Princeſs. All the Lords and Gentlemen of Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty being
advertiſed thereof, either pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared themſelves to dance, or to run at the
Ring. <hi>Vincia,</hi> a little after the fruit was ſerved, roſe from the
table, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king as if ſhe would go into another chamber, ran ſtraightway
down to the door, and beckened to one of <hi>Clerio</hi>'s Gentlemen to come
ſpeak with her, who came preſently to her, and then ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired him to
tell his Maſter ſhe would ſpeak with him; preſently he came down,
hoping for ſome wholeſom counſel; ſo ſhe took him by the hand,
ſaying,</p>
            <p>My Couſin, there is a Wedding to to day, where they are to run
at the Ring, and to have a Dance, thither is your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs to go, fail
not, be ſure to be there attired with white and mallow-flower Colours, for
ſhe liketh them very well; you have time enough to do it, for ſhe is not
yet ready, becauſe it will be late be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they run: I ſhould attire you my
ſelf, but for fear it ſhould be known; but <pb n="64" facs="tcp:115129:37"/>you know
well enough how to inveſt your ſelf with your accoutrements; be ſure to
be ſecret in the deſign. Adieu.</p>
            <p>My Couſin, quoth <hi>Clerio,</hi> I humbly kiſs your hands,
and beleeve not that I ſhall be any more ſick. <hi>Vincia,</hi> after ſhe
had made him a courſie, ran up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and commanded the Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maids to
prepare and bring to her Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs one of the richeſt Gowns, that ſhe
might be moſt neat and glorious, and adorned with the moſt precious Jewels
that could be deſired, that ſhe might as well ſurpaſs in glory as
beauty the moſt honorable Lady of the Aſſembly. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Clerio</hi>
had given to a many Taylors an infinite number of pieces of Stuffs, with
directions after his own invention for the making of his Sute, which was after
the Turkiſh faſhion, of white Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Cloth, imboſſed with precious
Stones, with Studs of Silver, his Buskins ſilvered to the middle leg; his Hat
a pure Beaver, with a Hatband of great Pearls, with his Hair curled full of
<hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prus</hi> Powder, two ear Jewels ſo fair and <pb n="65" facs="tcp:115129:37"/>great, that they were worth ſix thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand crowns, in a word, as
fine as fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers could make him, his horſe was a Spaniſh Gennet white, the
mane and tail fairly painted, with a great plume of Herons Feathers in his
forehead; his capariſon of ſilver Cloth lined with Sat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, and all other
accoutrements exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rich and graceful, his Mask had a Diamond at the mouth
worth four thouſand Crowns, that it was impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to find his Paragon,
ſo gallant and compleat was he in every punctilio. Juſt as he went out of
the gate, he put himſelf under a Silver Cloth of State, born by ſix Nymphs,
every one having their horſe capariſon'd after the ſame manner as his,
with a Page at their ſides to hold the horſes bridles in their hands.</p>
            <p>In the mean time his Miſtreſs, after ſhe was gloriouſly
arrayed, went to the Dance to enjoy ſome contentment by the ſight of ſo
many fair Ladies, which ſight was neglected to behold ſo graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a Prince
in ſo graceful attire. This Sun of Love and Beauty, by taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way 
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:115129:38"/>from them their vain glory, cauſed them to contemn
themſelves: After they had danced a long time with <hi>Venus</hi> Viols,
<hi>Mars</hi> his warlike Trumpers ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a different tune, which made
theſe Ladies betake themſelves to the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, to ſee thoſe Cavaliers
which were attired for to excel in ſumptuouſneſs, and to aſſay to get
their graces with the Ring. After a number of them were paſſed by, behold
<hi>Clerio</hi> came in his pomp with ſix Trumpeters before him in the ſame
Livery, who going from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Cloth of State, appeared to be the King of
thoſe Lords, and the Lord of the hearts of thoſe beauteous Queens, who
ſeeing him ſo gorgeouſly accou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, did aſſiſt his courſes and
his loves with the deſires of ſucceſs from love and fortune. Then when he
came near <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zia,</hi> who as well as the reſt earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to
know him, he bowed his Lance to the ground, then he lifted it up again, and
made his horſe ſhew a thouſand pretty tricks, being as gloriouſly
amor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of his new Harneſs, as was <hi>Clerio</hi> of <pb n="67" facs="tcp:115129:38"/>his Miſtreſs who gave the ring. In his turn he ſet himſelf on
a career, with an incredible deſire to bear it away, the which gave to the
Ladies as much hopes as deſires of his good ſucceſs: As ſoon as ever he
had got it, their ſhouting, joys, clapping of hands, did accompany the honour
and homage a thouſand Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets rendered to his glory; of thirty which ran,
there were but two others which ran it in, who did expect they alſo ſhould
have ſome part in the Ring, for which end they diſputed with him, and all
three ſet forward on a ſecond courſe; <hi>Clerio</hi> doubted he ſhould
loſe it, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to accuſe him, who ſhould get, of ſomewhat or
other, (as they have but barren brains which cannot pick a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel when they
intend to fall out,) but Fortune, which fought for him, quickly put the
queſtion out of Controverſie, and at the third courſe he gained the Ring
and the honour from his Rivals. This happy Victors triumph happened to his
hearts contentment, and to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of all theſe Ladies looking upon 
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:115129:39"/>him: Drawing near to his fair Princeſs, he made his
horſe go on with moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent curvets, to the admiration of her and all
that ſaw it; then coming under her chamber window, he bowed his Lance, and
then preſented it to receive the Ring. <hi>Lozia</hi> and all the Ladies
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to know him, deſired him to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mask himſelf; but he very nobly
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed himſelf, and after five or ſix cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vets with his horſe he
kiſſed his Lance, and preſented it to her again. <hi>Lozia</hi> was ſo
deſirous to know who it was, that ſhe knew not what to do; but fearing
ſhe might anger him with her delay, drew a ring off her finger worth two
thouſand Crowns, and putting it upon the end of his Lance, ſaid to him,</p>
            <p>Noble Knight, if you are ſo gallant as I eſteem you are, you
will come at night to my houſe to the dance with this ring upon your finger.
He bended his Lance down to his Page to have him take the ring off the end of
it, which he did amorouſly kiſs before he put it on his finger; then
turning to <hi>Lozia,</hi> ſaid,</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:115129:39"/>
            <p>Fair Princeſs, I am ſorry that I am not as worthy to wear this
ring, as I have been fortunate in the taking it from ſo many noble Gentlemen,
and from your gracious hands, which I honour more then any thing in the World,
to put it upon mine, which cannot deſerve ſo ſpecial a favour and high an
honour, before they have drawn a thouſand times a ſword in your
ſervice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lozia</hi> valued this ready Reply more then the ring ſhe
gave him. <hi>Clerio,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had took his leave of her, rode to the
Knights which attended for him, of whom he took his farewell, after they had
praiſed his merits, and congratulated his proſperous ſucceſs. As
tender-heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed mothers bewail the loſs of their dear children, ſo did
<hi>Lozia</hi> and theſe Ladies bemoan the departure of this Captiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of
their hearts with moiſt eyes and burning breſts. The night after, the
ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this glorious Sun did ſoon poſſeſs its wonted darkneſs,
which cauſed <hi>Lozia,</hi> as afflicted as fair, to deſire the Ladies to
come to her dance, rather that ſhe might <pb n="70" facs="tcp:115129:40"/>ſee her
ſervant, then for any deſire ſhe had to dance: ſeeing themſelves
honor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo far by her as to be intreated, they could not refuſe but honour
her with their company, every one deſiring by amorous favors and courteous
behavior to win the love of this Knight, who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced them to affect him, who
being fill'd with glory and at liberty, acknowledged nothing to be the Law of
love but what came from his beloved <hi>Lozia.</hi> But <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio,</hi> what
haſt thou to do with ſo many deſigns, parties, and amorous ambuſhes
that theſe Ladies lay for thee? How wilt thou hide thy ſelf from thoſe
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptive eyes which are infatigably open to behold thy actions, graces, and
noble deportment? Thou ſhalt be as much troubled to fire thy ſelf from
their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate paſſions, as contented to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor thine own, as inequal
in the ſubject as in beauty and merit. <hi>Clerio,</hi> I leave thee in the
midſt of thy new conqueſt loves and amorous entertainments, and go to his
Miſtreſs, who having bid the Ladies Goodnight, went alone into her
Cloſet, <pb n="71" facs="tcp:115129:40"/>where in the midſt of her ſolitude ſhe was
accompanied with ſighs, ſorrows, and a thouſand love-deſpairs. Poor
child, it is not with dry eyes that I write thoſe of thy cruel dolour, which
draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a pearly dew from thine eyes, thoſe dainty Suns, notwithſtanding
their fires and flames. It is obſervable, that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture admirably in its
variety is ſo ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened in this, that ſhe will never give any other
entrance to affliction then that of joy: for thoſe ſweet and delicate eyes
which did lately give ſo much content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to this young Princeſs by the
ſight of her <hi>Clerio,</hi> thoſe ſame eyes now pour out briniſh
tears in his abſence, and that noble Soul which did ere while burn with a
thouſand ardent flames, is now in peril for the ſame cauſe to be drowned
in ſorrow.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vincia</hi> doubting that her Miſtreſs might be in ſome
amorous Paroxiſm, went to her to take away all imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of her fooliſh
fancy, which might diſtemper her body, and to pacifie her mind,
diſcompoſed with paſſion: After <pb n="72" facs="tcp:115129:41"/>ſhe had looked
upon her a little while, ſet in a Chair with her eyes in tears, thoſe tears
in fires, thoſe fires in ſighs, thoſe ſighs in love, and love
transformed into a thouſand cruel deaths, of which this fair <hi>Lozia</hi>
did one day expect a joyful life, ſhe ſpoke, to make her a little forget
her inſupportable afflictions, thus:</p>
            <p>Madam, if I did know that my Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin, whom I honour and affect
with all my heart, would have been the cauſe of your ſo long diſtempers,
I ſhould have been very glad if he had never come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Spain:</hi> I do
beleeve, that if he was not ignorant of your paſſions, he would be too too
ſenſible of them, to the peril of his life: What reaſon have you thus to
perplex your ſelf? Do you deſire what you already have the
poſſeſſion of? Do you ſeek for a ſhadow, being already in the
ſhade? If you look but a moment upon him, he awaketh all night for your
ſervice: If you do this honor to him as to love him never ſo little, he
will humbly adore your ſweet beauty. Who hath more cauſe to complain,
either you <pb n="73" facs="tcp:115129:41"/>who have affected him but two or three days, or
he which hath been ſix moneths in love with you, with a thouſand fears and
ſad apprehenſions of your diſlike of his earneſt affections? You are
the foundation of all his hopes, and the baſis of his building, and ſo if
you fail him he is utterly undone; but inclination only cauſeth you to
eſteem him, who for more weighty cauſes doth honour and adore you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lozia</hi> anſwered her, <hi>Vincia,</hi> it is not all to
be what I am; ſome among ſo many fair and honorable Ladies will affect him
as well as I, who being able with more liberty and conveniency to oblige him
then I, can or will allure him by their voluntary enforcements, and the hopes
of a thouſand liberties and privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges he ſhall enjoy, and prerogatives
wherewith he ſhall be inveſted. Judg but how diſcontented he will be to
come hither, when I dare not diſcourſe with him half the time of his
ſtay: Do you think he will change his <hi>French</hi> freedom into a
<hi>Spaniſh</hi> thraldom? His counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, <pb n="74" facs="tcp:115129:42"/>actions and
conditions carry li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty writ upon the front of them in a legible character;
but above all, this hath moſt of all troubled me, that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not work it out
of my head, but that it was not he that gain'd the Ring, which all the Ladies
did ſo much admire: His grace, habit and behavior give me more then a
ſuſpicion it was: After I had given it him, he returned me thanks in the
moſt eloquent words that ever I heard, which all the other Country Sots could
never have had the underſtanding to invent: I diſcovered under the Mask
almoſt his voyce, his ſpirit, &amp; his eyes. <hi>Vincia,</hi> I pray thee
take away from me this doubtful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and heſitancy, for I ſhould be very
ſorry if it were another; but there could not be found ſurely any which
could ſo much reſemble <hi>Clerio:</hi> It is the extream puſſion I
have for him which rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth theſe ſcruples in me: Thoſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
geſtures of his horſe, thoſe pleaſant poſtures, and thoſe
delightful courſes, thoſe rich habits, ſo delicately accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated with
his rich train, give me <pb n="75" facs="tcp:115129:42"/>ſome aſſurance that it was
<hi>Clerio</hi> alone which was thus accompanied: But that I wonder at, is, how
in ſo ſmall a time he hath been able to prepare ſuch Veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as
fine as thoſe which have been this moneth providing.</p>
            <p>It is true Miſtreſs, ſaid <hi>Vincia,</hi> that it was
<hi>Clerio,</hi> and that <hi>Clerio</hi> only was worthy to be honoured with
ſo happy a fortune and honorable a favour as was that.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vincia,</hi> quoth <hi>Lozia,</hi> I have requeſted him to
come to the Dance to night, but I hope the Ladies will not know him; for you
know, though they ſaw him diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed with his Mask, that yet they were
exceedingly in love with him; then how ardent will their affections be, when
they ſee him as he is in his beauty, without the dark lanthorns of his
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe?</p>
            <p>Madam, my Couſin hath ſo much knowledge of your greatneſs
and of that honour he ſhall have by being your humble Servant, that either
you wrong your ſelf by eſteeming him ſo highly, <pb n="76" facs="tcp:115129:43"/>or
him, to think he hath ſo little judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as not to be able and willing to
conſerve the honour of your good grace, on which hinge hangeth all his
happineſs. But whilſt you are here, the Viols wait for you in your
chamber.</p>
            <p>'Tis well ſaid <hi>Vincia,</hi> let us go eat a bit, elſe we
ſhall not have ſupped before the company come. I give you a charge of all,
keep the honour of the houſe, if you pleaſe: I would I had given away a
thouſand crowns rather then invited theſe Ladies to come, my breaſt is
all on fire within me: but it is a fault, and ſaying theſe words, went and
ſate down at the Table. The Viols, as ſoon as they ſaw her, played till
the Muſique of her voyce did ſilence them by return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thanks to them, and
welcome to an infinite number of Lords and Ladies, who were come betimes to
have place to behold the Dance: ſhe was fain to acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modate her ſelf to
their humor, and convert her ſorrow into a ſhew of joy, which of all
actions the greateſt perſons can moſt cloſely ſimulate to delights, 
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:115129:43"/>even thoſe which do diſpleaſe them, by whoſe means
with their amorous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion they often procure the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of
their deſires. This fair Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs commanded her muſique to play ſome
pleaſurable tunes, and turning to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the greateſt Lord that was there,
ſaid, This will keep you from thinking it long before the company comes. This
rare conſort of your ſweet words is as melodious harmony as the ſound of
the Viols. <hi>Vincia</hi> in the mean while was buſied in lighting perfumed
candles for the Hall, and preparing ſeats for the Ladies to ſit down in;
there were railes round about to hinder the influx of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly people, within
which the Lords were, who intended to Dance: there was on one ſide a place
deſtinated for the Viols, made like a ſcaffold very compleatly, and
artificially built: a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny precious things were burned in this hall, the more
honorably to receive this beautifull Goddeſs; who riſing from the Table,
took with her an infinite number of Ladies richly attired, who 
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:115129:44"/>did admire at the excellent and delicate furniture of the
Hall, the hangings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all of ſilk and gold, pure and fair, excellently
inamel'd with pearls, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched with precious ſtones, the Lamps and
candleſticks of gold of Parvaim, the Wainſcot was moſt artifically
gilded, as likewiſe was the ſeiling; the ſhelves moſt fitly faſhioned
by a dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous artificer, the Chimney of Marble and jaſper. This ſplended
greatneſs of a maid ſurpaſſed the mageſticalneſs of the pureſt
French Lillies of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, as ſumptuous as they were.
When this fair Princeſs was ſet in her chair, all the Ladies,
Marqueſſes, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſes, Viſcounts, and Barons ſate down in their
places according to their quality about her. Two of the Gentlemen, like
Captains of the Guard, hind rod the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders; the Viols played divers
French Dances, which <hi>Loxia</hi> danced very well, as likewiſe did the
other Ladies, who learned by her imitations. To put every one in order, ſhe
prayed the Prince of <hi>Dondonne</hi> to lead her, and all the other 
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:115129:44"/>Lords to take their Ladies; ſhe Danced ſo
ſuperlatively well, that her eyes, her beauty and her graces, did
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibly affect the hearts of all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. After the firſt Dance
was finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſhe deſired the reſt to continue their delight whileſt
ſhe ſat down and reſted her ſelf, only to have more freedom to think
upon her ſervant, from whom ſhe ſaw a Page ſpeaking to <hi>Vincia.</hi>
A little while after ſhe cal'd <hi>Vincia</hi> to know what the matter was.
<hi>Vincia</hi> cold her, that her Couſin ſent her the <hi>Bon ſoir,</hi>
and deſired to be excuſed for his non-appearance, becauſe he found
himſelf not very well. <hi>Lozia</hi> taking this for real truth, was very
much troubled for his diſeaſe, ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thizing with him in his ſorrows,
and for the fruſtrating of her expectation of his preſence. But the good
Lord came not long after to dance a moſt famous dance with a moſt noble
company. As they entered into the houſe, there was raiſed by the Lacquits
and Pages a great noiſe, which was ſoon heard by the company, who were much
amazed to ſee their gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry. <pb n="80" facs="tcp:115129:45"/>They were all in two
Clouds ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly artificially made, in the one there was ſix clad like
Knights, with Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Cloths, with their Miraſſes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly made, and
their Plumes of Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which <hi>Mars</hi> did lead; in the other were
ſix arrayed like Goddeſſes in white Silver Cloth, ſewed with golden
thred, in which were interlaced the pictures of <hi>Lozia,</hi> with a
thouſand ſuch delicacies, and this ſame was lead by <hi>Clerio,</hi> who
repreſented love, very richly attired with his wings, quiver and arrows;
twenty Viols and twelve Pages in <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zia</hi>'s Livery, each with two white
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumed Torches, entered before, and ſtood directly oppoſite to
<hi>Mars</hi> his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; two other Pages, which had as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectable voyces as
could be deſired, one clad in white, the other in blue Sattin, played upon
the Lute in the middle of the Hall over againſt <hi>Lozia</hi> five or ſix
tunes marvelouſly well in the honour of <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Gupid:</hi> As
ſoon as they had done, the Cloud of <hi>Mars,</hi> covered with Trophies of
Arms and Torches, which <pb n="81" facs="tcp:115129:45"/>repreſented in their light all
ſorts of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, began to flaſh out with Thunder, Lightenings,
Thunderbolts, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the ſweeteſt Melody of the Sackbuts, Harps
and Lutes, with the ſweet voyce of Love, which, full of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters, Flames,
and Trophies of Love and Stars, did ſhew exceeding delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. Ceaſing
their dainty ditties, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous noiſes, theſe two Clouds were opened to
let every one of the Maſquers out; and when one was gone out of each, they
inſtantly cloſed again, and began their Flaſhings and Muſique until all
were gone out after that manner, and then they began their Dance in ſeven or
eight different airs, with a world of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters and Figures interlaced, which
cauſed them all to admire. As it was done, <hi>Mars</hi> and Love fought, and
after a world of blows, <hi>Mars</hi> perceiving his eyes wounded with a bolt
which Love had ſecretly ſhot at him, in ſtead of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing daunted by ſo
ſweet a wound, was rather madded and vexed that he ſhould be thus
vanquiſhed, and ſo fell on ſo <pb n="82" facs="tcp:115129:46"/>courageouſly, that
coming ſomething near him, he ſnatched away <hi>Cupids</hi> band, which
blindfolding his eyes, cauſed him to ſtrike a many fruitleſs blows: But
Love recovering his ſight, the loſs of which had made him ſo often fail,
took one of the ſharpeſt arrows in his Quiver, and ſhot it ſo directly,
that piercing the very heart of his enemy, he gained his honour and his life.
The gods which were upon the Heavens of theſe Clouds, quitted their divine
Seat, and came pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to put the band again about <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pids</hi> eyes,
leſt this divine Archer ſhould ſee to diſpeople the Heaven of gods, the
Earth of men, and that ſharing in the Empire of <hi>Pluto,</hi> they ſhould
dwell to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in thoſe obſcure ſhades. <hi>Jupiter,</hi> as the
greateſt and alſo the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed of them all, ſpake thus unto
them:</p>
            <q>Mortals, who not being able to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend and dive into the
reaſons of divine actions, offend us often by your rebellious ignorance: That
it may not happen to you to fall any more into this diſobedience, know, 
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:115129:46"/>that Love having taken its original from Heaven, doth yet
retain ſome ſparks of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity among you earthly humanes; and that you are
not to give him battel, but obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience: If we bind up his eyes, it is not to
blind his ſight, but only make him a little more ſubmiſsive, and that we
may ſet him free when any one is ſo fooliſh as to diſdain and contemn
ſo great an infant, as to equal his ſtrength to his.</q>
            <p>Theſe words ended, the gods return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into their proper places,
and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> to demonſtrate his anger, ſuddenly did eclipſe the
glorious Sun, and in ſtead of light, gave the company a ſweet ſhowre of
rain, with hail of Pearls and Sugar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plums: Whileſt the company was buſie in
the gathering of them, this ſuperbe Vanquiſher receiving the Trophies and
the Laurels that <hi>Mars</hi> had upon his head, went to ſacrifice them with
his heart and liberty to the beauty and graces of the fair <hi>Lozia,</hi> and
kneeling unto this ſacred Deity, after he had kiſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the border of her
Gown, ſpake as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth:</p>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:115129:47"/>
            <p>Fair Princeſs, I give unto your eyes all the honor of this
glorious Conqueſt, to whom I conſecrate theſe Laurels, as an
acknowledgment of this favour, and theſe Mirtles, as the firſt homage after
my new ſubjection: If their ſweet flames have inflamed my Soul with an
amor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous heat, their dainty darts, ſerving themſelves with my hands, have
utterly extinguiſhed it in mine enemies. I hope this Mask hath not given you
any miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt of my love; and beleeve, what I have untertaken, hath been to
deceive this peoples eyes, and not yours, my fair Princeſs: To which I
wiſh, that the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent flames that I have received there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from theſe ſix
moneths, and the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment which I ſhall keep always rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for your
ſervice, may be as continual as is my countenance, which carrieth both my
love and heart upon the front thereof, as the moſt weighty teſtimony of the
truth of my words. And ſaying ſo, he plucked aſide his Mask to ſhew
<hi>Lozia</hi> his face, and put it on preſently again for fear of being
ſeen of others. <pb n="85" facs="tcp:115129:47"/>The Lord and Ladies ſuppoſed it to be
ſome Country Gentleman, and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions thought he would tell her ſome
tale, and ſo without ſuſpicion he decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved both the one and the other,
and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued his diſcourſe, ſaying; Fair Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs (whoſe Sun may
it never ſet) permit me this day to call you the Miſtreſs of my
deſires, and all my wills together, that I may have the honour to receive the
honorable quality of the moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſervant of yours, which I ſhall
e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem as great a favour as your beauty; your graces and merits making you
the nobleſt Paragon of all others, give me deſires and knowledg of ſo
great an happineſs, ſwearing to you by the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulleſt oaths a
conſtant Lover can make unto his Miſtreſs, That I will rather dye then
diſobey the leaſt of your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, and ſhall honour nothing more
then the flames of love and paſſion which your beautiful eyes have kindled
in my breſt: If love transformed into your face, animateth my heart with the
ſweet heat of your eyes with an impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <pb n="86" facs="tcp:115129:48"/>deſire to
ſerve you; the vertue under the ſweet object of your merits, much more
raviſhing by its admirable attractions, takes away, with a thouſand
delectable tranſportations, my will from my will, to leave me nothing but the
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to honour you for ever as the Soul of my Soul, which giveth motion
to my life by that of mine affection.</p>
            <p>Fair goddeſs, were I to write thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate loves, I would not
invoke, as did the ancient <hi>Apollo,</hi> for his divine heat; but would come
unto thy fair eyes, to animate ſo effectually my ſpirit and my pen, that my
diſcourſe may be ſo grave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſweet, that it may delight the moſt
delicate ears of thoſe which read it, and ſo learnedly grave, that the
moſt eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſpirits may highly eſteem it, who ſeek rather for the
ſteeled points of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons to ſatisfie their minds, then the quaint and
alluring ſweetneſs of fair words to pleaſe their ears, which is the
outward bark of all unto generous ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. Princeſs, I finiſh my words
to give beginning to thoſe which you ſhall ſay to your ſervant.</p>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:115129:48"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Clerio,</hi> ſaith <hi>Lozia,</hi> your noble ſpirit and
your gallantry are ſufficient not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to oblige <hi>Lozia,</hi> but the
greateſt and graciouſeſt Queen in the world, to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour your love and
merits: I perceive my ſelf ſo happy in the amorous aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of your
affections, that I ten times more eſteem the poſſeſſion of your good
grace, then of twenty Realms.</p>
            <p>A Lady which ſate ſomewhat near her, not dreaming of any thing
leſs then of theſe Loves, came nearer to hear their diſcourſe, to whom
<hi>Lozia,</hi> breaking her diſcourſe, ſaid, without any appearance of
alteration; Madam, you do me a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to come hither, for this hour hath
this ſame Maskman talked to me in <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> and I know not what he
ſaith, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I pray you be mine Interpreter, and you will eaſe me of a
hard task. This <hi>Lozia</hi> ſaid, purpoſely that <hi>Clerio,</hi> who
ſpeak perfect <hi>Italian,</hi> might quckly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ride her for her broken
language, and drive her away for ſhame. He being of a quick apprehenſion
knew his Miſtreſſes intentions, and ſo began to tell an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred 
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:115129:49"/>jeſts, which ſo amazed this poor woman, that ſhe knew
not what to do, but that others did come to participate of the pleaſure,
which <hi>Clerio</hi> ſeeing, ſtole away, and unmasked himſelf, and went
to his Couſin, with whom he diſcourſed till the Dance was ended, of the
content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he had received by the honour <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zia</hi> did him to accept
his ſervice with ſo much aſſurance of affection, that he e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed
himſelf the moſt happy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in the world, <hi>Vincia</hi> had not
ſpoke three or four words before ſhe was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted by <hi>Lozia,</hi>
who was roſe from the ſport to go to bed, who alſo thereby put a period
to all the delights of that night. <hi>Clerio,</hi> like an officious Couſin,
and affectionate ſervant, led <hi>Vincia</hi> by the hand to <hi>Lozia</hi>'s
chamber, to whom he gave the <hi>Bon ſoir</hi> of the day, that he had
received from her fair eyes in the midſt of his obſcure darkneſs; and
ſo contented, he withdrew with a living hope; and ſhe contented, ſtayd in
the midſt of a thouſand deſperate paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:115129:49"/>
            <p>The Souls of theſe amorous Lovers floated all this night among
an hundred different irreſolutions, which hope and deſpair did equally
agitate, going from the Port to ſhipwrack, from dangers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to aſſurance,
from aſſurance into an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous confuſion, which thoſe only that have
been in the like labyrinth can either comprehend or complain of.</p>
            <p>Knights, for whom alone Love ſeems to have been lawfully
inſtituted, which others make uſe of rather by borrowing and a deſtinated
neceſſity, then any vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary conſent of Nature, which with an ambitious
jealouſie of it ſelf aſpireth always towards perfection: Knights (ſay
I, the eldeſt ſons of Honor) who by your honour and gallantry draw delight
from the ſweet frequentation of Ladies, from whom you learn what you are,
with a thouſand delicious dalliances, which are far from popular
converſations, who bear from your birth the defence of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies graven upon
the ends of your ſwords with the hands of honour and vertue; make proof of
your merits, with <pb n="90" facs="tcp:115129:50"/>a juſt acknowledgment of the
obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which you owe to this Sex. Now when you ſee a numberleſs
number of indiſcreet people, blame this beautiful and noble Princeſs, which
love, not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, hath ſo far engaged, who knowing that her kindreds
obſtinacy was incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patible with her innocent affections, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth her
fooliſh ambitions to marry her love with her contentment, and
<hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio</hi> with <hi>Lozia,</hi> not in a laſcivious, but in a loving
and legitimate Wedlock.</p>
            <p>Brave Lovers, whileſt I have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed with theſe
Knights, the night is paſt away; but I come with the Sun to you, to know,
after I have given you a good morn, what you will do all the day.</p>
            <p>This fair Princeſs was no ſooner a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waked, but a Gentleman from
the Duke of <hi>Blanfort</hi> came to her to deſire her to lend him her
Muſick that he would have played of after the Dance to a very fair Lady, with
whom he was to baptize one of his friends ſons; that if ſhe pleaſed to
take the pains to go thither, the Duke of <pb n="91" facs="tcp:115129:50"/>
               <hi>Blanfort</hi>
would accompany her. <hi>Lozia</hi> ſeeing that this was an opportune
occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to entertain her ſervant at leaſure, ſaid to him;</p>
            <p>Sir, I entreat you to tell mine Uncle, that I humbly kiſs his
hands, and that I ſat up ſo long yeſterday, that I have been ill all
night, and ſhall keep my bed to day, but my Muſick and all I have is at his
ſervice if he command it.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as the Gentleman was gone, ſhe ſaid to
<hi>Vincia,</hi> Have not I done well? Very well, Miſtreſs, quoth ſhe.
Then ſaid <hi>Lozia</hi> ſmilingly, I muſt ſee my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant after
dinner, I pray you make me very ſpruce, and attire me as neatly as it is
poſſible; for I ſhall never ſee any one whom I ſo much honour, or to
whom I deſire to make my ſelf ſo acceptable, as to him. I will,
Miſtreſs, anſwered <hi>Vincia.</hi> And preſently gave her her morning
Gown, that ſhe might go attire her head by the fire ſide; Her Coif very
hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, with flexures in it for her hair to paſs out moſt compleatly
curled, full of powder and hair-jewels; ſhe had two <pb n="92" facs="tcp:115129:51"/>Pendants on her ears worth fifteen thouſand Crowns, a Chain of
Pearls three times about her neck worth as much; <hi>Vincia</hi> gave her a
Caſſock of white Sattin, lined with a mallow colour, with precious Stones
ſewed therein, the Buttons of which were fair Beazils; upon the Sleeves ſhe
put two admirable Chains of Gold, on the ſide a Box of Ammel covered with
Jewels, wherein was her Pourtraiture of an invaluable worth: up and down the
Chambers they ſet Candles and ſuch things on fire, fill'd with Musk and
Ambar, to perfume the room: Her Bed was ſo richly hung, as likewiſe was her
Chamber, that one would have thought Love ſhould have entered in there, or
elſe that Love, in love with the fair <hi>Lozia,</hi> did make his continual
abode among thoſe ſweet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights. <hi>Clerio,</hi> who likewiſe
deſireſt to render thy ſelf acceptable to thy Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, provide for
thy ornament; her exquiſite delineaments, her beauty, her graces, her fair
eyes, to defend thy liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, rather then ſplendid habits to raviſh 
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:115129:51"/>her of hers, which ſhe hath amorouſly ſacrificed to
thy merits and gallantry, after her heart had inſenſibly deprived thee of
thine, thine of hers. Idle Mig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards, you are ſo long attiring your
ſelves, that dinner hath waited for you, till it is as cold as you are hot
and full of fire: Go take your refection of thoſe delicates prepared for you,
as needful for the nouriſhment of your bodies, as that of love to your
divinely inflamed Souls.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lozia</hi> went to dinner preſently, but none was ſuffered
to come in but <hi>Vincia</hi> and <hi>Charlotta</hi> to ſerve her, that the
belief of her diſeaſe might exempt her from importunity, and give her
opportunity to entertain <hi>Clerio,</hi> who came in preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after ſhe
had dined, and after he had ſaluted her, he ſpake thus:</p>
            <p>Fair Princeſs, my paſſion is ſo violent, that rendering to
me the ſight of the faireſt Ladies in the world as foul, the more ardently
to honour yours, I fear that mine <hi>in fine</hi> may be as diſpleaſant to
you, as that of yours is now impatiently <pb n="94" facs="tcp:115129:52"/>deſired of mine
impatient deſires: But methinks in diſanimating my ſelf of my Soul
through mine eyes, you enliven me again with the ſweet flames of yours, which
cauſe me to feel as many amorous burnings in mine heart, as there are
beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and graces in your face, moſt fair, accompanied with a thouſand
and a thouſand dolorous or amorous ſighs: After I had diligently ſought
for my li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and my heart in an hundred pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, I came at laſt to find it
guided by my love in the middle of your graces and beauties; and if you are not
content with ſo honorable Trophies, I muſt look if I have not yet
ſomething free from that conqueſt which you have made in my Soul, that I
may conjure it by your holy name to yield homage and adoration to you, that
having nothing but love in me, I may more honorably and humbly ſerve you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clerio,</hi> anſwered <hi>Lozia,</hi> you are too noble and
gallant to enter into ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt of your ſelf, and I too much
af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with your love and merits to keep <pb n="95" facs="tcp:115129:52"/>you very long
in the quickſands of doubtings. I beſeech you to beleeve, that although
many Princes do me this favour as to affect me, yet that I honour your love
ſo much more, as it is more deſirable then all theirs. <hi>Clerio,</hi>
live in the belief of this, that as you are the firſt, ſo the moſt
faithfully loved by <hi>Lozia</hi> in all the world: Fortune yeſterday gave
you this ring on your finger, and <hi>Lozia</hi> gives you to day her heart and
her pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traiture, which is in this Box, as an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of her true
affection, wear it for my ſake I deſire you: And giving it him, gave him
likewiſe a kiſs, which did ſo amorouſly conjoyn their lips and loves,
that from thence their ſouls and hearts were knit in an inſolvable
knot.</p>
            <p>This is not all, quoth <hi>Vincia,</hi> Miſtreſs, to give
ſuch happy beginnings to ſo firm amity, if withall you do ſeek out ſome
ways to continue it; you know that all the reſt in the houſe depend upon
your Uncle, and I only ſolely upon you, who will rather dye then expend my
life up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any other ſervice; and ſo neceſſary <pb n="96" facs="tcp:115129:53"/>is
our diligence in the purſuing of our affairs for to preſerve my life and
ſafety with my Couſins, that our neglect to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard them will ruine us: I
know, if you will both be adviſed by me, how to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuate this preſent
buſineſs, as to finiſh it to our contentment: Thoſe which are
paſſionate, if they are prudent, muſt be governed by the directions and
dictates of thoſe which are exempted from it. <hi>Clerio,</hi> you muſt, as
I have formerly hinted to you, continue your ſimulation of loving me, I am
neither ſo old nor ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>favour'd yet that none will credit it, that every time
you are diſcourſing with my Miſtreſs, they may think it is to employ
her in our loves: You muſt firſt col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue with the Duke of
<hi>Blanfort,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Doudonne,</hi> becauſe it is needful
that they ſhould be firſt gulled who are moſt intereſted in the
buſineſs. And my Miſtreſs, you muſt not make any ſhew of ſorrow;
and if you cannot altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther impede its entrance into your heart, yet let
wiſdom ſo curb your natural in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, that you diſcover it not unto 
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:115129:53"/>your familiars, which that you may the better perform, from
henceforth make as if you loved reading, which will be an excuſe for that
little alteration any one ſhall perceive, and ſtill have a little book in
your pocket, which take out and read when you cannot rid your ſelf of thoſe
troubleſom thoughts which break in up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you; and for my part, leave me to
act that without the advantage of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lozia</hi> and <hi>Clerio</hi> concluded of this as their
ſecureſt courſe, and intended to purſue it, and ſo received
reciprocal aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurances of each others affections with abundance of joy and
contentment: That as thoſe Lands which are neareſt to the Sun have their
fruits ſooneſt ripe and ready to gather; ſo theſe two faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Lovers
equally paſſionate, did in the midſt of their ardent flames approach ſo
near to love, that by the vertue of its vicinity, like the Orange trees, they
put forth in few days the leaves, flowers, and fruit. Hence-forward did this
ſuperſtitious Lover ſo dote upon <pb n="98" facs="tcp:115129:54"/>his Miſtreſs,
that he kiſſed her hands now a thouſand times, which before he durſt
ſcarce look on. Conſider noble Knights, that Ladies ſometimes cauſe you
to paſs beyond the narrow limits of your firſt condition, honorably to
enlarge them. Knights, I beſeech you once again, as a teſtimony of your
birth and breeding, to reſpect Ladies, and think not you have leſs honour
for the honorable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of this duty, then you ſhould have if it were
freely tendered by the greateſt of the world: They are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of making you
more glorious and renowned then all your own perfections and deſervings:
There is nothing in the world ſo perſwaſive as them, who with their words
and actions do inchant our wills, and deprive our ſenſes of their proper
function, and with their eyes give life and motion to our ſpirits and
deſires: We are the true Chameleons of their humors, who receive in our
hearts all the various and vive impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſo fair and divine
objects: Theſe are thoſe glorious Suns, whoſe ſplendid 
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:115129:54"/>light our eyes cannot any more remove, then can our hearts
the heat thereof, which they receive according to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of our
minds, and not the ſtrength of theſe divine and amorous beams: If there is
any ſpirit ſo agitated; that it never could ſee the dawning of a glorious
day, nor a ſparkle of light as a pledg of future Sun-ſhine, ſuch muſt
ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther weep for, and complain of, then any ways deſire and expect a
favorable aſpect from theſe frowning &amp; malign Planets: Briefly, he who
knoweth not this gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, is accounted more fit for a Clown, then a
Courtier, and a ſimple Sot, rather then a Noble man: Thus far are we
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted to them, they give grace to our actions, eloquence to our words, a
day to the obſcure ſhadows of our ſpirits, a Soul to the hearts and
ſpirits of thoſe which have none. Fair Ladies, little (but little indeed)
gods upon Earth, who are the abſoluteſt Commanders of men, tyrannize not
over Nobility, who alone knoweth and eſteemeth your merits: Live ſo
diſcreetly with them, that none <pb n="100" facs="tcp:115129:55"/>may ever go
diſcontented from your company: It is no graceful thing to make your ſelves
penſive, on purpoſe to excuſe that ſottiſh humor wherewith you are
troubled in the company of thoſe whoſe ſociety you do not affect: All
thoſe whom you ſee are neither your Husbands nor your Couſins, that you
ſhould impatiently bear their imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Cannot you courteouſly
entertain a Gentleman which will be gone within an hour, without a diſcovery
of rancor or malice, or at leaſt contempt? Do not make ſigns to your
conſorts, nor brabble and tattle with them without ſufficient reaſon,
whileſt any Gentleman is in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with you, which will make him
think you do deride him, rather if he be a Sot, then if a ſweet-behavior'd
and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous Gentleman; for fooliſh per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons will expound all texts to
their own diſadvantage, and thence proceed ſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing words and netling
ſpeeches, which well-bred women ſhould avoyd as a dangerous Precipice,
which always bringeth fears or hurts: Frequentation <pb n="101" facs="tcp:115129:55"/>with
fooliſh company is a contagious air, that will infect the moſt perfect
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, and taint the moſt unſtained honour; this gives the firſt
motion of life to the calumnies and opprobrious ſpeeches which active men,
fruitful mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and well-fed nurſes do bring forth and hatch up. Thus fair
Ladies, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite theſe unhappy accidents, I ſet your ſouls and hearts
at liberty from inthral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to any, but honor all and above all the Nobility
who draw their ſwords in your ſervice, who is of the ſame quality as you,
your Sex only making the differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and thoſe whoſe ſpirit and parts
you do ſometime miſpriſe, do often en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into your ſervice advantaged
by their means only. If fire hath neither the quality nor the name of fire,
ſo long as it is contained in the ſtone which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives it; your vertue
likewiſe is not truly vertue becauſe of the ſecret poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
thereof, but becauſe of the publique cognizance that there is had of it: Men
have not the nature of gods, they know not the cauſe but by the effects in
view. <pb n="102" facs="tcp:115129:56"/>Flatter not your ſelves, your honour is not your
own, if it is not in the mouths and hearts of thoſe that frequent you: It is
an excellent Pourtraiture hung up for future memory, and painted with the
immortal hands of Vertue in diſcretion, like to that of the moſt
affectionate of your ſervants, which you amorouſly carry in a Box, as a
Trophy of your beauty, and a pleaſant object for your eyes: But this divine
Painter is ſo jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of this moſt exquiſite piece of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufacture, that
he puts out theirs who go about never ſo little to diſpraiſe it.
Therefore, Ladies, I deſire you to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers when you are in company, and
e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver your own when you are alone. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieu, my Ladies, for I hear <hi>Lozia</hi>
calls me, and reprehendeth me as well as you for ſtaying ſo long to write
the faults and defects of the moſt part of women; I have ſtole this time
from her to give it you, and ſhall not be ſorry for it, willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taking
all the reproach to my ſelf, that all the profit of the robbery may be
yours.</p>
            <pb n="103" facs="tcp:115129:56"/>
            <p>Fair Princeſs, I went into the other chamber to diſcourſe
with the Knights and Ladies, which durſt not come in to you for fear of
diſpleaſing you; they have imbarked me ſo far in talking, that the night
hath come before the end of our diſcourſe began; therefore I intreat you to
excuſe me, if their pleaſurable ſociety hath ſtayed me longer then I
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended and ought to have been there; I did imagine that the ſight of
<hi>Clerio</hi> was ſo contentful to you, that you were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different as to
other objects. But, fair goddeſs, recite a little of the joys and ſweet
tranſportations and raviſhing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſies that your ſpirits have received
af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the aſſwagement of the tempeſtuous Sea wherein you have been
toſſed. When I think, that at the appearance of <hi>Clerio,</hi> Lord
Paramount of thy graces and beauties, thy eyes have poured out as many tears
for joy, as they had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly done for trouble and deſpair; methinks I ſee
the inhabitants of a City take up their arms, as well to honour the arrival of
their Prince, as to fruſtrate the <pb n="104" facs="tcp:115129:57"/>aſſaults of their
adverſaries. <hi>Lozia,</hi> dry up this pearly dew with a ſparkling beam
from thy beauteous eyes; re-aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume thy former ſerene vizage, which was
enamel'd with ſo many beauties and graces; make calm the paſſions of thy
Soul, which were raiſed by the wind of the afflictions and ſorrows of thy
<hi>Clerio.</hi> Wilt thou be willing it ſhould be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to him, that he
prepareth in lieu of delights and contentments, dolours, ſorrows, ſighs and
tears, for that perſon whom he honours and eſteems more then any perſon
in the world? Let this be enough, that he alone mingleth his life with his
love; make for him with thy delicate hands a Crown, as the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of the
moſt faithful and perfect Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers that ever was.</p>
            <p>Whileſt ſhe was in theſe ſad tears and ſorrowful
ſighs, yet ſweet imaginations, <hi>Vincia</hi> came to tell her of the
arrival of the Prince of <hi>Doudonne.</hi> This unwelcom news did cauſe as
great an alteration in her heart as in her face: This antipathy of fire and ice
did couple ſo perfectly <pb n="105" facs="tcp:115129:57"/>well her beauties and graces,
her Lillies and Roſes, her love and diſcretion, her ſmiles and her
frowns, that her Couſin could not diſcern any alteration in her
countenance: but ſhe ſeemed ſo much more beauteous to him, as ſhe was
more then uſually richly attired, which did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite him to a more fervent
deſire to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain her. This poor Princeſs in this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtine conflict,
between hatred and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, contempt and reſpect, overcame triumph a
thouſand times in a moment, enjoying as much ſatisfaction from the
contemplation of the gallantry and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity of <hi>Clerio,</hi> as ſhe did
trouble from the unwelcom view of her Couſin; who did ſo vehemently
importune her to ſpeak of love, that ſhe was forced to make as if ſhe was
ſick, that ſhe might be rid of him. <hi>Vincia,</hi> who knew her
Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes deſign, ſaid preſently, Miſtreſs, you having been
ſick all day, this talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing maketh you worſe. The Prince of
<hi>Doudonne</hi> thinking that was the reaſon, returned home
preſently.</p>
            <p>My good <hi>Vincia,</hi> how tedious is <pb n="106" facs="tcp:115129:58"/>it to
an honeſt and modeſt woman to hear a Sot talk of love, who will then moſt
wilfully wait on them when they are moſt ſhamefully repulſed and
neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by them? I had rather a thouſand times dye, then that my Couſin,
who is as ignorant and as impudent as others, ſhould importune me ſo long
with his irkſom loves, which are as diſpleaſant to me as himſelf. What
likelyhood is there that without grace they ſhould hope to obtain gracious
and graceful Ladies? without a noble and heroick ſpirit, they ſhould oblige
their divine Souls to be obedient unto their deſires? without beauty and
love, and thoſe charms, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements and delicacies in their eyes, wherewith
the Heavens and Nature do graciouſly endow ſome, they ſhould win the love
of thoſe Ladies in whom theſe and many other invaluable gifts of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
are in a ſuperlative meaſure? <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia,</hi> I intreat thee to make our
ſouls and loves as free as they are fair and divine: It is from thee onely
that I expect ſo great a good, who art able to go for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward 
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:115129:58"/>with ſo high and perilous an enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe.</p>
            <p>Miſtreſs, ſaid <hi>Vincia,</hi> ſeeing you do me the
honour as to command it me, I will declare what I think moſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;
and I hope my counſel will be ſo profitable, that our undertaking ſhall
ſucceed according to our deſires. I ſhould like it well, if you would
tell e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very body, eſpecially your Uncle, that you will ſhortly compleat our
marriage, that the report of our nuptials may give ſome repoſe to your
loves, until ſome few days ſhall be gone; and when they think leaſt of
it, you ſhall know how much I watch for your ſervice: He can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not long
continue his conſtant repair hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but either your own folks, or the Duke
of <hi>Blanfort</hi> will be ſuſpicious: But in lieu of my nuptials, we
will ſolemnize yours in this manner as I will declare to you. You have an
hundred Villages where you have never been, the Prieſts whereof know you as
little as the great <hi>Turk;</hi> one of theſe days, making as if we went to
walk for our recreation with <pb n="108" facs="tcp:115129:59"/>a Coach, we will take a time
ſo fit for the purpoſe, that it ſhall be almoſt night when we come into
one of them, the Curate of which is as blind as he is old, and by that means
will not know you; and before we come to the place, you ſhall go a foot to
the Church door; the people preſently will aſſemble to ſee what is the
matter, and therefore will I pray you to command your Gentlemen and Damſels
to ſtay without to ſtop this preſs of people, under colour of divers ill
accidents which fall out at marriages by this means; and ſo being all alone,
the Prieſt ſhall eſpouſe you; during this time I will be hard by
vailed, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king as if I were <hi>Lozia;</hi> and ſo for this time you and
<hi>Clerio</hi> muſt give me that reverence and reſpect as is due to me,
that he might be the more confident of his opinion, and be ſure we will be
gone with ſpeed without over many Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies again into the Coach; and
becauſe I am taller then you, I will get made for you a pair of Pattins,
which render our highneſs and ſtature both alike: and as 
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:115129:59"/>I ſhall go to give you a Gown that morning, ask for one
without any taking notice of mine, which ſhall be ſuch an one as mine is,
which I will have made purpoſely, leſt the Prieſt ſhould diſcover any
thing by our Veſtments; and ſome days before you ſhall give your
ſervants order to dreſs and trim up the chamber at the end of the Gallery
juſt againſt yours, that from that time <hi>Clerio</hi> may lie with his
wife, and not his Couſin; and you ſhall intreat your Uncle to let you
likewiſe entertain <hi>Clerio</hi> into your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, that you may keep
me, and that you cannot by any means part with me, and he will eaſily agree
to this for fear of diſpleaſing you: and likewiſe to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie me, whom
he ſuppoſeth do employ my intereſt for his preferment, he will be very
glad to oblige <hi>Clerio</hi> and me, under hope of a remuneration of his
courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies; but when the buſineſs is ſo far ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced, we will
adviſe of a further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs.</p>
            <p>Fair Ladies, who do here peruſe the incredible proofs of
affection that <hi>Clerio</hi> 
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:115129:60"/>received from his Couſin,
call them not I intreat you by any other name then what the honour of your Sex
and her quality do oblige you to: Reſemble not the venomous Vipers, who cover
good food in mortal poyſon: But taking in good part theſe vertuous actions,
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that if ever you were in love, you have employed therein perſons
of leſs quality, dignity and deſerts then ſhe, who hath by legitimate
nuptials render<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the marriage of <hi>Lozia</hi> honorable, and full of
Roſes and ſweet delights, amidſt a world of thorns and perilous
appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions, putting her own diſcretion and affection as a Cloak under
her feet, that ſhe might tread upon the moſt danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and dreadful
difficulties with more ſecurity.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Lozia</hi> did expect the ſequel of <hi>Vincia</hi>'s
diſcourſe, which was as accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able as affectionate, ſhe was ſuddenly
affrighted to hear a great multitude of people coming, who followed a Prince
that came to ſee her and to ſerve her; ſhe could ſcarcely recall her
ſelf to her <pb n="111" facs="tcp:115129:60"/>ſelf, before he was come into the
cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: The Prince his name was <hi>Don Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio,</hi> who was a very pretty
and proper perſon, having beauty proportionable to his bigneſs, and riches
that exceeded both, which cauſed <hi>Lozia</hi> to eſteem him very much;
and although his love was not ſo delectable to her as <hi>Clerio</hi>'s, yet
becauſe of his diſcent and deſerts ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haved her ſelf ſo
diſcreetly, that he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped one day to enjoy the ſweet graces of divine
<hi>Lozia.</hi> Whileſt this Prince was in diſcourſe with <hi>Lozia,
Vincia</hi> like a good ſervant went to tell the news of this new love to the
Duke of <hi>Blanfort,</hi> who, after he had over-ruled his anger, returned
thanks to <hi>Vincia</hi> for this cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie, and ſaid to her theſe
words:</p>
            <p>Miſtreſs <hi>Vincia,</hi> I never doubted that my Niece could
merit and meet with a better perſon then my ſon: This belief, with the
deſires I have of her advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wound me with as many mortal ſtrokes,
as I have lively apprehenſions of it: This lawful affection hath ſo much
effect in the hearts of fathers, that <pb n="112" facs="tcp:115129:61"/>there is no way
which they leave unat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted, which may conduce to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and happineſs
of their children: I have hitherto endeavored to diſpoſe my Niece to this
marriage for her own and my advantage; but I honour her ſo ſo much, that I
will never oppoſe her will to fulfil mine. <hi>Vincia,</hi> I ſee that in
this I muſt bear my ſelf up more with the hope of your affection to me and
my ſon, then to any other thing in the world: Had not you better aſſiſt
me who am of the houſe, then a forreigner who will carry away all, and not
oblige you ſo as I intend and will endeavor? <hi>Vincia,</hi> wouldſt thou
forſake thine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient acquaintance whoſe affections are certain, to affect
new ones which are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain?</p>
            <p>Sir, replyed <hi>Vincia,</hi> I am ſo much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with the
honour of your love, that I eſteem my ſelf more happy to be your humble
ſervant, then to be a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion with the greateſt of this Realm: You would
do me wrong, if you ſhould judg me to be the occaſion that your 
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:115129:61"/>Niece doth not deſire this marriage as well as you; but
ſhe is yet ſo young, that ſhe knoweth not what is for her ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage; yet
will it not be amiſs to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der new love from getting foot in her heart,
which hath made me come hither to advertiſe you of it; I ſuppoſe you
would do well to take the pains to go ſee her, to interrupt the diſcourſe
of her new ſervant; go before without any ſhew of my following you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vincia</hi> having given him ſo hot an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larum, mockt him,
for thinking her on his ſide, of which ſhe made a ſhew, the more neatly
to gull him. This Prince, aſſured of her affection, undid himſelf by his
credulity: for <hi>Vincia</hi> could not lay a more firm foundation to her
deſigns, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what ſhould be raiſed on the ruins of the Duke &amp;
Prince, which cannot be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in the midſt of ſo much ſuſpicion
without the aid of diſſembled affection, which is the beſt of all bad
things when we do uſe it towards indifferent perſons, for the utility of
thoſe to whom we are engaged. <hi>Vincia</hi> was no ſooner come, 
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:115129:62"/>but <hi>Don Allio</hi> took leave of his Miſtreſs, and
then <hi>Vincia</hi> related all the diſcourſe ſhe had with the Duke,
which excited ſweet ſmiles in the face of <hi>Lozia,</hi> to hear how her
Uncle was out-witted: <hi>Vincia</hi> following her diſcourſe, ſaid
thus:</p>
            <p>Madam, this new love of <hi>Don Allio</hi> is the faireſt
occaſion that we could deſire to gull the Duke of <hi>Blanfort,</hi> who
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades himſelf that you bear affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to this new Lover; and I think
it beſt that you uſe him kindly, to increaſe his jealouſie; and he puts
great confidence in me, but his skill in the end will fail him.</p>
            <p>No ſooner had <hi>Vincia</hi> ſaid theſe words, but the Duke
of <hi>Blanfort</hi> entered with a very ſowre look; and <hi>Lozia</hi>
ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him in this eſtate, and remembering what <hi>Vincia</hi> had told
her, could hardly forbear laughing, but however ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frained therefrom. The
Duke of <hi>Blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,</hi> after he had asked her how ſhe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſaid to
her:</p>
            <p>My Niece, ſeeing that <hi>Don Allio</hi> (who is an indifferent
perſon to you) ſeeks for <pb n="115" facs="tcp:115129:62"/>your good liking, I deſire
you not to take it ill at my hands, if the deſire which I have for the
conſervation of our houſe makes me rather wiſh this fortune for my ſon,
then leave it to a ſtranger: I am confident that you are of ſo good a
nature, that this ambition will be no ways diſagreeable unto you, and that
you will rather make this natural electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to conſerve the honour and
greatneſs of your Predeceſſors, then the other, whereby you will loſe
it, diſuniting the good affection to your blood, which obliges all thoſe
that have underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and honour to retain ſome ſweet heat, which
rather animates their hearts to this lawful devoir, then to ſo unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral a
hatred. I have always been hindred to ſpeak to you by the reſpect which I
bore you, leſt I ſhould anger you; and if I had not feared you would have
care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly eſteemed of my diſcretion, I would have attended until your
own judgment and humor had given you the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to oblige me, and to
beſtow on my ſon the ineſtimable good of your favor, <pb n="116" facs="tcp:115129:63"/>whereby we might ſerve you through the whole courſe of our lives:
and if this is not your own pleaſure, do not in any wiſe think that it will
be mine, but that to the contrary I will employ all that could be to my own
particular good to render you more free, to the end that the loſs of the hope
of my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune and contentment may give you the poſſeſſion of yours,
which I hold a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times more dear then whatſoever may happen to me
in the world. <hi>Lozia,</hi> after all theſe fair ſpeeches, ſmiling,
an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered him:</p>
            <p>Sir, my birth and education teach me to honour all thoſe whoſe
merits and quality render them worthy to do this favour to love me. If <hi>Don
Allio</hi> came to ſee me, his ſight no more then others is not ſo full
of charms, that it hath power inſenſibly to violate my Reaſon and Soul to
any thing that is contrary to my will: My condition doth ſufficiently e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
exempt me from ſo religious a conſtraint, and my honour keepeth me
religiouſly enough within the free bonds <pb n="117" facs="tcp:115129:63"/>of vertue,
without your entring into this opinion, that the firſt view cauſeth love in
me. The ſame youth that makes me deſire the agreeable converſation of
ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt people, endues me with a mortal ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of theſe fooliſh
paſſions, as the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norableſt tortures of faireſt Souls; and when this
humor ſhall come on me, I have vanity and glory enough to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reach the
ambition and greatneſs of my Predeceſſors. But Sir, in ſtead of mine
let us commune of the nuptials of <hi>Vincia,</hi> which I ſhortly intend;
this will be a means to ſtay her in my ſervice, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that
<hi>Clerio</hi> will come, for otherwiſe I ſhall do nothing:
<hi>Vincia</hi> is my ſecond ſelf, without whoſe company I cannot live; I
pray Sir, uſe your utmoſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor to cauſe him to live with me, not
ſo much to ſerve me, as that I may thereby enjoy the company of
<hi>Vincia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Niece, quoth he, you have good reaſon, for you ſhall hardly
find ſuch an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; I will earneſtly entreat him, and I am perſwaded that
for your own ſake or mine I ſhall perſwade him to do it; 
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:115129:64"/>but he hath too many ſervants, which he will rather
encreaſe then diminiſh, and this is the worſt.</p>
            <p>No, no, Sir, anſwered <hi>Lozia</hi> to him; if he had as many
more I would defray all charges, and I ſhall think it an honor to have ſuch
a Gentleman ſo near me; I am more afraid that he will not come, then of the
charge: <hi>Vincia</hi> ſaith, He is very rich, and it very well appears
ſo, for he keeps as great a Port as any. Lord of this Country. At theſe
words <hi>Clerio</hi> entered, whereupon they all laughed, that he ſhould
come ſo oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunely. After the Duke of <hi>Blanfort</hi> had embraced
<hi>Clerio,</hi> who came to ſalute him (to oblige his Niece) prayed him to
do him the favour to promiſe him one <hi>boon. Clerio</hi> feigning his
ignorance, promiſed him to perform what ever it ſhould be his pleaſure to
command him. Then ſaid the Duke, That which I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat of you is on the
behalf of my Niece, to oblige her and my ſelf not to take <hi>Vincia</hi>
from her; and becauſe it will be inconvenient for you being married 
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:115129:64"/>to live apart, we pray you and all your train to come live
here, and my Niece will defray their charges; you ſhall be no more
conſtrained then if you were by your ſelf; you and <hi>Vincia</hi> ſhall
ſit at her own table, and your Servitors ſhall be equal unto hers: I pray
you do this for my ſake; and if I can for the future do you any ſervice, I
will do it with as much affection, as if it were for my own children. Sir,
anſwered <hi>Clerio</hi> to him, the greateſt honour which I ever hoped
for, was to be in the ſervice of ſo great a Princeſs, and commanded
thereunto by that Prince, who above all others in the world I moſt honour, to
receive this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour: but I find my ſelf ſo unprofitable for her ſervice,
and whatſoever people I have, rather ſerve for charge then profit:
nevertheleſs, Sir, ſeeing that Madam and you command me, I will effect for
you all that you requeſt. The Duke of <hi>Blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi> infinitely
ſatisfied, took <hi>Clerio</hi> by the hand, and brought him to ſup with
him, where he entertained him with all the delicates that might be, and ſwore
to <pb n="120" facs="tcp:115129:65"/>him an eternal amity: After ſupper he ſhewed him
his ſtable, which was very magnificent, and gave him one of his faireſt
horſes, to oblige him to his part. <hi>Clerio,</hi> after he had
ſubmiſſively gratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated him for the honour which he had afforded him,
took leave of him, and went to viſit his Miſtreſs, who paſſed away
the time with <hi>Vincia,</hi> at the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of the Duke of
<hi>Blanfort.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Come, come, my Knight, ſaid <hi>Lozia</hi> to him; now may I
call you mine, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you are given to ſerve me by my Uncle the Duke of
<hi>Blanfort.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Madam, ſaid <hi>Clerio,</hi> he is extreamly liberal, for he
hath ſo much honoured me, as to give me one of his beſt horſes.</p>
            <p>It is very well, ſaid ſhe in laughing; he gives to take, but
his liberalities are unprofitable, for he ſhall loſe both his preſent,
and hope, if I do not deceive my ſelf.</p>
            <p>I beleeve Madam, ſaid he, that he hath given it me rather for a
deſign, then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by his natural inclination, not having done ſo much
ſervice, as to <pb n="121" facs="tcp:115129:65"/>oblige him thus to gratifie me.</p>
            <p>Doubt not, ſaid <hi>Lozia,</hi> for he is fuller of inventions
then any mortal creature, and for all the good entertainment he ſeems to make
to you &amp; <hi>Vincia,</hi> he wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth your deaths, but I hope he ſhall
be as far from his account, as I nigh to mine; but <hi>Vincia,</hi> what's thy
opinion of it?</p>
            <p>Miſtreſs, when it pleaſeth you all things are ready, and
nothing is wanting, but your Commandment. I leave all to your diſcretion,
anſwered the fair <hi>Lozia</hi> to her.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clerio</hi> being inſtigated by an amorous impatience,
ſaid to his Couſin, Feſtinate I pray you <hi>Vincia</hi> to conſolate a
Lover, who dyeth quotidianly a thouſand times by the refulgency of thoſe
ſweet flames which proceed from the fair eyes of her whom I ſatisfactorily
adore: it is to imitate the Deities to aſſiſt thoſe who pray us: the
moments in this furious paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion are ages to me of dolorous accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations,
yet are they as agreeable to me as this fair Princeſs who animates you. My
Couſin, there are ſix or ſeven days <pb n="122" facs="tcp:115129:66"/>fully
compleated, ſince I was firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſted by theſe inquietudes for your
fair Miſtreſs, whoſe beauty is the ſource from whence proceeds my
impatient paſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vincia</hi> anſwered, The hope of acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo happy and
ſo nigh a poſſeſſion might mitigate the impatiences of your Soul; but
the amorous are excuſable, who relinquiſh reaſon as an ignomini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
charge, giving the reigns to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, to purſue more lightly their
paſſions, to which by force they give themſelves, rather then by
diſcretion, ſeeing themſelves exempted from knowledg, loving better to
have a blind guide, then to remain alone in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of ſuch ſavage
deſerts as our ſenſes alienated from admiration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lozia</hi> interrupting <hi>Vincia,</hi> ſaid to her
ſervant <hi>Clerio,</hi> I love being ſo amor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: And obliging him by this
honor, ſhe gave him her fair hands within the curl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hairs of thoſe of
love; it is idolatrous for him to bend this knot before ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny graces and
formoſities, of which he <pb n="123" facs="tcp:115129:66"/>ſhall ſoon be
Poſſeſſor, having with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, dying a thouſand times by her for
many ardent flames: As a Cork ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times elevateth it ſelf, and then
ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mergeth under the water; ſo this hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, full of vanity, forgetting
his firſt eſtate, left himſelf to be ambitiouſly tranſported above
ſo many courteſies and amorous ſubmiſſions of ſo great a
Princeſs; and to teſtifie to her his violent paſſion, commended his
elocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions by a profound ſuſpiration.</p>
            <p>Fair Miſtreſs, whom I reverence as the moſt holy and
ſacredſt of all terrene Deities, and to whom alone quotidianly I offer a
thouſand ſecret ſacrifices from my heart, I conjure you by your fair
eyes, the moſt capable puiſſances, to move you to accord to me the
requeſt which I will make you in the behalf of your <hi>Clerio,</hi> which
might furniſh me with ſo many amorous diſpences, as theſe eyes, graces
and beauties make by their ſo long ſojourn at my heart: It behoveth that I
now pay by my death a thouſand amorous Creditors; if thoſe 
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:115129:67"/>agreeable hoſts of my Soul take not pity of him, who for
the more honorable reception hath engaged his liberty and his life, this would
be to pick a Roſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the time with rigorous hands, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their being
vulnerated by the thorns of compaſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clerio,</hi> my friend, what wouldſt thou that I do? Thy
loves and thy merits have ſo much power upon me, that I cannot denegate any
thing unto thee which is agreeable; when thou wilt, I will give thee the
beauties and ſweet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectations, which this yong bodypoſſeſſes with
ſo entire poſſeſſion, as that which thou hadſt of my heart, of my
loves, and my Soul, ſince the firſt day that I had the honor to ſee thee.
<hi>Clerio,</hi> go on in this credence, and I entreat thee not to handle me
ſo rigorouſly, unleſs you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to make me dye cruelly; but cauſe
thou that <hi>Vincia</hi> accord our content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with our amorous cupidities,
and then thou mayſt know that my ſpeeches are as veritable as my
paſſions. <hi>Vincia</hi> extreamly ſatisfied, ſaid to her, It ſhall 
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:115129:67"/>be then after to morrow. I conſent to it, ſaid
<hi>Lozia,</hi> from the voyce of theſe two hearts, which have but one will
and one ſoul; and that one paſſion which was equally in two, is equally
both in the one and the other. I am of opinion Miſtreſs, that when it doth
adveſperate, you ſend one of your Gentlemen, to pray <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur de
Blanfort</hi> to come to morrow to dine with you, and your Couſin to come
with him; when he riſes, entreat him to aſſiſt at our nuptials after
dinner; if he is aſtoniſhed at this inopinate novelty, you may tell him
that you never could obtain this favor of me before this time; but ſeeing it
is now my humor, you will not give me the leaſure to repent, and becauſe it
is already late, go retire your ſelf, that you may riſe betime in the
morning. <hi>Clerio</hi> following her coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, gave the Goodnight to his
Miſtreſs, and received from her a thouſand new loves, in exchange of the
which, he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained her all that night, hindering her from ſleeping; the
day being come, he went to find <hi>Mounſieur de Blanfort,</hi> who 
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:115129:68"/>booted himſelf to go ſee his Hawk fly two or three
hours, where being come, the Duke made him good enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment, and after
ſome ſpeeches of meriment, ſaid to him,</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Clerio,</hi> I pray you be of the party, if you are not
nigh your nuptials. Madam, my Niece, yeſternight ſent to me to pray me to
dine with her; I pray you kiſs her hands on my part, and tell her, that I
ſhall be there at my return, and ſeeing it is for your honor, my ſon
ſhall be there alſo; and if you will, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you are not of this
Country, I wil bring thither ſome Lords my friends. <hi>Clerio</hi> ſaid to
him, Sir, you very much oblige me, I cannot refuſe the honor of theſe fair
offers. After ſome other ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches he took his leave, and the Duke of
<hi>Blanfort</hi> mounted a horſeback: <hi>Clerio</hi> went ſoon to find
his Miſtreſs, who was a bed, where he went to render her his common
ſervice: this fair Princeſs had as yet her hair careleſly diſperſed,
where love that night took his releaſe, as a Bow far bent might go with more 
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:115129:68"/>impetuoſity and violence to wound the faireſt Souls
with ſome, as a But to ſo gallant an Archer, whom he putteth from one to
another with his mortal jaculations, whereby he arreſted the eyes of thoſe
who ſaw him, under the form of a fair vizage, or would harken unto him under
the charming dulcitude of a fair reputation: This colour, theſe eyes, theſe
ſmilings, theſe hands, theſe graces, this neck, this throat, were a
<hi>Scylla</hi> and <hi>Charybdis,</hi> where the gallant'ſt hearts af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
their naufrage were amorouſly caught: In the mean time theſe two Lovers
entertained themſelves: <hi>Vincia</hi> ſent to ſearch for the Violins,
to pray the Ladies to put them in tune; then ſhe went to ſee whether the
fair <hi>Lozia</hi> was yet dreſt, which this day put on her rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
Veſtments, as ſhe who had the moſt intereſt in the feaſt; ſhe had
not curled her hair, and powdered her locks, before <hi>Mounſieur de
Blanfort</hi> arrived, and with him the Prince of <hi>Doudonne,</hi> and ſome
other Lords, that he had entreated to come with him, who being hungry, 
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:115129:69"/>by reaſon of the venation, went into the Kitchin, which
was ſo good, that he ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there ſo long till <hi>Lozia</hi> was
habilled, to the end they might put the Partridges in a diſh, of which they
had only ſeen the feathers in the air. <hi>Clerio</hi> deſcended alſo to
entertain the company, attending this fair Princeſs, who feſtinated rather
to ſee her ſervant, then thoſe: I have ſo many times ſaid, that ſhe
was as agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably fair as you might imagine; that the Artifice (which is the
husband of this fair woman, that is, Nature) had made her attain the perfection
of Pulchritude. They paſſed all this day in feaſting, dancing, muſicks,
&amp; a thouſand different ſorts of pleaſure, and conſummated the
nuptials of <hi>Clerio</hi> and <hi>Vincia,</hi> who was very well accountred,
falt, young, and of good grace, who had had the quality of Lady of Honor (which
was given ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily but to ancient women) rather for merit then age. The
night being come, all retired themſelves, being in general very well
ſatisfied to have ſo well paſſed their time, and leaving theſe two
Lovers in <pb n="129" facs="tcp:115129:69"/>their deſired ſolitude, who ſeeing
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves thus bereft of all ſociety, entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves in a
joint entertainment. Fair eyes which ſpeake in your ſweet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards,
wherefor do you deprive the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders &amp; my pen of its function, &amp; ſo
ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fair Ladies from the agreeable plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of your amorous
diſcourſes; which I cannot recount amorouſly enough: I not having had the
honor to be an auri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular or ocular teſtator of their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations: you
are cauſe that a world of honeſt men make uncivil quarrels to my ſpirit,
which might not very diliciouſly be delivered of the divine conceptions of
your amorous ſouls, that you have hidden from it under your ſilence: but
one thing conſolates me which writing not but for your fair ones, who have a
million of Cavaleers ſlaves to your beauty; you diſcover in an inſtant
theſe amorous cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters, that the learned paſſion hath of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
explicated if the ſots and the deform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed raile againſt the miſprizal that
I make of it, fair ones remember you defend me, or make retreat to your
gracious <pb n="130" facs="tcp:115129:70"/>beauties and my ſpirit, which ſhould be of
the roſe and lillies, and my pen of thorns for the conſervation of both: I
cannot accompany my book every where to aſſiſt it, but I hope this good
office from your grace and beauties which ſill all the world with reſpect
and honor, and which from their amorous beams diſcipated the inſupportable
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcretions, as from the nocturnal obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity which troubled the
furtherance of their ſociety.</p>
            <p>Theſe Lovers were not at all troubled to give to their eyes the
ſelf ſame plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure they had a thouſand times received, if
<hi>Vincia</hi> had not in a manner ſeperated them by force and cauſed this
fair Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs to go to bed, that ſhe might not be ſick on the next day.
The night was ſoon paſſed. And <hi>Lozia</hi> according to the deſigns
of <hi>Vincia</hi> eſpouſed her <hi>Clerio,</hi> as I have already told you
moſt happily: It was ſomewhat late when they return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which was the
cauſe that theſe dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels being ſurpriſed with ſo ſuddain
nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phials, did rather think of preparations <pb n="131" facs="tcp:115129:70"/>to bed then to
ſupper, for <hi>Vincia</hi> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaned her ſelf like a married woman,
and <hi>Clerio</hi> did uſe the like fallacie to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive theſe poor
Damſels.</p>
            <p>So as the Chamber was made ready <hi>Lozia</hi> commanded
<hi>Vincia</hi> to go to bed, who ſeemed unwilling, and in the end ſhe
anſwered her, Madam, I will not go to my bed until I have had the honor to
ſee you in yours: <hi>Lozia</hi> who well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood her deſign, ſoon
accorded ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, to the end that the Damſels might no more return into her
chamber, unleſs it were one whoſe name was <hi>Charlotta,</hi> who came out
of <hi>Fance</hi> with <hi>Vincia,</hi> and was well acquainted with their
actions: <hi>Vincia</hi> gave the good night to her Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris and accompained
with Damſels went to bed, the Damſels after they had ſeen her in bed did
all depart, to give place to <hi>Clerio;</hi> who in ſtead of going to bed to
his dear Couſin (to whom he was ſo much engaged) kiſſed her and went to
his Spouſe who extreamly deſired his company.</p>
            <p>Theſe two paſſionate Lovers raviſhed <pb n="132" facs="tcp:115129:71"/>with their raviſhments, being in bed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether remained dumb, to
give audience to their loves, in the middle of a thouſand ſweet kiſſes:
which perfectly united their hearts, their eys and their mouths. Thus theſe
two amorous ſouls remained capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated in one anothers arms all this night;
until the morning: When as the radient beams of <hi>Phoebus</hi> golden light
provoked them both to ariſe from their beds.</p>
            <p>Ladies, I ſhall not here relate at large the ſeveral
paſtimes and exerciſes that were diurnally practiſed during the
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of this wedding, which laſted for the ſpace of eight days with
great magnificence for the honor of <hi>Clerio;</hi> but I ſhall return to
<hi>Don Allio</hi> who continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his amorous ſuit, and the Duke of
<hi>Blantfort</hi> perceiving that <hi>Lozia</hi> regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him with a
pleaſing aſpect, thereupon began to doubt that his purpoſes would have no
good end, and therefore he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to carry her away violently and marry
her to the Prince of <hi>Doudonne</hi> his ſon, that he might be exempted
from thoſe continual alarums which he dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <pb n="133" facs="tcp:115129:71"/>Wherefore, he came one day in the company of thirty men to viſite
<hi>Lozia;</hi> but principally to put his horrid deſign in execution.
<hi>Lozia</hi> was aſtoniſhed to ſee ſo many men, and did not know what
to imagine, and the Duke of <hi>Blantfort</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching uttered this
diſcouſre to her.</p>
            <p>My Neice, I have been advertiſed, that <hi>Don Allio</hi>
ſhould eſpouſe you on this day, and therefore I (ſhall be much blamed
if it ſhall ſo happen) having the honor to be entruſted with the care of
your perſon: If this evil had happened to you, I ſhould have died for
grief, and therefore ſo ſoon as ever I was made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted herewith, I
came to you to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer my Caſtle unto you as a place of ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: and if you
will honor me ſo much, as to let me have your company therein, I will
deſire no greater office during your abode there, then to be your keeper.
Theſe honeſt Gentle men have done me the honor to accompany me, that you
may retire your ſelf in greater State. <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zia</hi> diſſembling her
deſign returned an anſwer to him in theſe terms.</p>
            <pb n="134" facs="tcp:115129:72"/>
            <p>Sir, amongſt all the Obligations, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I am bound to you I
account of this, as the chiefeſt, and becauſe I will make appear unto you,
that I greatly deſire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing that thou ſhalt think conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent; I will
inſtantly go dreſs my ſelf, to go with you, and therefore I would
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat you (if ſo be you ſhal think it good) to take a turn or two in the
garden until I am ready, which ſhall be very ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: The Duke of
<hi>Blantfort</hi> did accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, and ſhe preſently ſent for
<hi>Clerio,</hi> to whom ſhe ſaid;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clerio,</hi> now is the time wherein there is need for you to
ſhew your courage and affection towards me; can you ſuffer this Villain to
ſnatch me out of your arms: Go now (if you love) to <hi>Don Allio</hi> and
both of you gather together the moſt of your friends that you can, and kill
this Cuckold and his followers, who will not be ſufficiently aſſured to
defend themſelves, and let it ſuffice you that you have <hi>Lozia</hi> and
her love for your fortune and guide. There were ſix of her Gentlemen at that
time preſent, <pb n="135" facs="tcp:115129:72"/>wherefore ſhe cauſed them to be called
to her, to whom ſhe uſed theſe ſpeeches; Sirs, the aſſurance of
your fidelity and the deſire I have to do you good, is the cauſe you are
Gentlemen of my houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, which place many do importunate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſire; will
you not then diſpute my liberty and your fortunes againſt this Traitor the
Duke of <hi>Blantfort,</hi> who is below to carry me away priſoner? They all
anſwered yes: Go then my friends ſaid ſhe, and do what <hi>Clerio</hi>
ſhall deſire you: at your return every one that doth well ſhall have 2000
crowns. They all preſently departed with this reſolution, that they would
fight couragiouſly: <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zia</hi> then called <hi>Clerio</hi> and ſaid to
him, my Dear, let me once more kiſs you and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow a Ribbon on you, that
you being filled with love and fortune may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible.</p>
            <p>Fair on (anſwered <hi>Clerio</hi>) if your fair eyes have
beſtowed life on my love, ought I not to hope that your favors wil give
vivacity to my honor; which with a million of Charms hidden under this 
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:115129:73"/>Ribon, will render me invincible. When he had ſpoken
theſe words to <hi>Lozia,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing full of ambition, valor and love; he
went from her and reſolved with theſe ſix Gentlemen of <hi>Lozia's</hi>
and two of his own, to ſet upon the Duke of <hi>Blanfort</hi> who had 30; and
he would not call <hi>Don Allio,</hi> leaſt he ſhould have buthalf the
honor of the victory. He went into the Armory of <hi>Lozia's</hi> deceaſed
father, and there he cauſed theſe Gentlemen to take each of them a
Cuyraſe, leſt the thought of ſo many men ſhould aſtoniſh them, and
before he departed he ſaid to them.</p>
            <p>Sirs, to teſtifie the care which I have of your lives, and the
deſire which we have this day to do good ſervice to our Miſtreſs, hath
been the cauſe that I have prayed every one of you to arm your ſelves.
There is never one of us who car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries notwritten in his front, the death of ten
of theſe Raſcals, who are come not with a courage to fight, but with a
pernicious deſign to rob us of our miſtreſs and our fortune, which wholly
depends on her. Conſider Sirs, the cruel affront which <pb n="137" facs="tcp:115129:73"/>theſe ſlaves give us, and the ſhameful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach which we
ſhall receive of all the world: where ſhall we finde ſhadows obſcure
enough to hide us from this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach? Can there be a better deſign for us to
ſhew our courages in, then in defence of our Miſtreſs? Our devoir
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites us thereunto, our ambition carries us thither, and our honor obliges
us ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. Then I pray Sirs let us go, and you ſhall ſoon ſee thoſe
people in diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: Let us diſpatch then, ſaid they all with one voice.
<hi>Clerio</hi> and his ſmall company went preſently into the place where
the Duke of <hi>Blanfort</hi> was, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with his followers; and
advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before the reſt of his Company with his ſword in his hand, he
ſet upon them, &amp; in the end he himſelf killed the Prince of
<hi>Doudonne,</hi> who for a time defended him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with much vivacity: his
Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons likewiſe behaved themſelves with ſo gallant demeanor, and
ſhewed ſo appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, that their carriages were excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and in ſhort
time they killed a good part of them, and put the reſt to flight. 
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:115129:74"/>The Duke of <hi>Blanfort</hi> fled with them, and they
could not follow them ſo ſwiftly as they deſired, by reaſon of their
armor, <hi>Lozia,</hi> who ſaw this tragedy out of her window; being extream
glad of the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſucceſs of her <hi>Clerio,</hi> went before and embraced
him, and his followers one af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter another: She gave <hi>Clerio</hi> a Picture
worth 50000 crowns, and to each of the others 1000 crowns, and a Spaniſh
horſe worth 500 crowns. The Duke of <hi>Blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi> being inraged at this
affront, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſparing for the loſs of his ſon, cauſed twelve of
<hi>Lazia's</hi> towns to revolt againſt her ſervice.</p>
            <p>But this great and courragious Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, who had three or four
Millions in the Coffers of her deceaſed father, in ſtead of being amazed
laughed at this fooliſhnes, and ſoon gave commiſſions to raiſe
forces, provided munitions of war, and levied foot, with ſuch diligence, that
within fifteen days ſhe had 1000 horſes, 15000 foot men and 20 pieces of
Cannon; her Army being raiſed, ſhe gave the charge thereof to
<hi>Clerio,</hi> and <pb n="139" facs="tcp:115129:74"/>gave him money to pay ſix moneths
wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to his ſouldiers. She took an oath of fidelity of all the Captains,
and prayed <hi>Clerio</hi> to go and beſige the place where the <hi>Duke</hi>
of <hi>Blanfort</hi> was retired, with expreſs charge to bring him alive or
dead.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clerio</hi> took leave of this fair Princeſs after a
thouſand ſweet and dear em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracements, a thouſand kiſſes and a
thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand tears, a thouſand ſights and a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand joyes, which
<hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Cupid</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually drew from their hearts. Whileſt he
conducted his army, <hi>Don Allio</hi> being advertiſed of the need
<hi>Lozia</hi> had of her friends, without ſaying a word rayſed 5000
horſe-men, and ſix thouſand foot-men, with eight pieces of Attillery, and
in this equipage went to viſit his Miſtriſs; who being informed of his
coming, went before in her Coach that ſhe might ſee his Troops. He
himſelf being mounted on a fair Spaniſh Geniet, went before all his Troops;
and no ſooner had he heard that his Miſtreſs was in the Coach, but he
diſmounted to go kiſs her hands. <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zia</hi> 
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:115129:75"/>underſtanding hereof, in ſign of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor cauſed her Coach to be
opened, and kiſſed him in recompence of his ſervice and affection which
he bore her. After <hi>Don Allio</hi> was ſeated in the Coach with her he
ſaid.</p>
            <p>Fair Princeſs I am much vexed that I was not with you to aid
you, at the time that the Duke of <hi>Blanfort</hi> came to you ſo well
accompanied; and if <hi>Clerio</hi> had the life of my Rival, I might at
leaſt have had his fathers for my part: But ſeeing that my croſs fortune
hindred me in ſo good an occaſion to render you good ſervice; I humbly
entreat you favora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to receive my friends which I offer to you: who are no
leſs affectionate to your ſervice then your <hi>Allio,</hi> who hath as
much paſſion and love for your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, as your beauties and eyes have
fire and flames for my ruin, they burn me and command me with ſo amorous and
ſweet Tiranny, that my obeyſance and ſervitude are more honorably
agreeable, then the moſt abſolute commandments and moſt free liberties.
Fair one, we are <pb n="141" facs="tcp:115129:75"/>come hither to render this firſt homage
of our affection, to receive the honor of your commands. <hi>Lozia</hi>
anſwered him thus.</p>
            <p>Sir, I finde my ſelf much obliged to you for ſo much
courteſie and charge, as you have put your ſelf to, to teſtifie your
affection to me. I know not how to refuſe theſe fair Troops, who ſeem to
be ſull of triumphs. I have already made <hi>Clerio</hi> General of my army,
to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence him with the honor of ſo fair a charge, for the honor which he
hath ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in doing me ſo ſpecial a ſervice. But as for your troops,
you are ſo gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, that I will not have them be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by any other
General but your ſelf.</p>
            <p>Madam, (ſaid <hi>Don Allio</hi>) I am not come to you in hopes
to be General of an Army, but to render you my ſervice; and if Fortune will
favor me ſo much as to make my ſervice profitable to you, I ſhall be much
honored. When he had ſaid thus, he asked <hi>Lozia</hi> to give him a favor,
ſhe being deſirous to pleaſure him, took off one of her garters which was
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:115129:76"/>bordered at the ends with pearls, and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it on his arm
ſhe ſaid: I deſire that it be as happy to you, with as good a will I give
it you. He mounted on horſeback, being extreamly contented, and depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to
his Souldiers who ſtaid for him, he ſent all his Captains to do reverence
to <hi>Lozia,</hi> who becauſe ſhe would oblige them to her ſervice, gave
them her hands to kiſs, which was an extraordinary fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor. <hi>Don Allio</hi>
departed and went to joyn his forces to thoſe of <hi>Clerio's,</hi> who went
before to meet him, and offered him the Command of his Army, but he thanked him
for this honor; and ſaid to him, I give my ſelf and friends to you; then
<hi>Clerio</hi> embraced him, and told him that he was his ſervant, and
<hi>Clerio</hi> asked him if he would lead the Rear, or the Van guard. <hi>Don
Allio</hi> deſiring to fight often, deſired to have the conduct of the
Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard. Then <hi>Clerio</hi> ſet his Army in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile aray, and went to
beſiege the Duke of <hi>Blanfort,</hi> who was in one of the beſt places in
the Country, which the deceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed father of <hi>Lozia</hi> had cauſed to be
for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified <pb n="143" facs="tcp:115129:76"/>as the moſt aſſured place of retreat. The
fortifications of this place were ſo ſtrong, that it was in a manner
account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed impregnable.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Clerio</hi> aproached, the Duke of <hi>Blanfort</hi>
iſſued forth, but was forced to retire; but in the end he was ſo blocked
up by ſea and by land, that it was impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for a Lackey to come
forth; and they had ſome quotidian bickerings with the enemy, and the Duke of
<hi>Blanfort</hi> in the town did much damage to <hi>Clerio's</hi> Army by his
pieces of Cannon, but <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio</hi> did timely prevent it with much
dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, notwithſtanding all his endeavors he continued in the ſiege
ſo long, that in the mean time, the Queen of <hi>England</hi> ſent a great
Army into Spain, which landed without any repulſe, and the King being
ſurprifed, loſt many towns before he could fortifie one. The Captain
Gener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of the Engliſh Army ſent two Lords to <hi>Clerio,</hi> to treat of
peace with him, or at leaſtwiſe a Nutrality: At the ſame time the King of
Spain ſent to his Couſin <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zia</hi> to aid him with her forces.
<hi>Clerio</hi> 
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:115129:77"/>gave the charge of the Siege to <hi>Don
Allio</hi> and went to his fair Miſtriſs, to ask coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of her, after
their accuſtomed im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracement <hi>Clerio</hi> ſaid to her,</p>
            <p>Miſtriſs, I remember that I have read a Fable which ſays,
<hi>that whileſt two great Maſtiffs fought for a piece of fleſh, a little
dog got it away.</hi> You may here ſee the like occaſion, that whileſt
theſe two puiſſant enemys fight with one another, it will be an eaſie
matter for me to triumph over them both, they both call me to their aid, but
this ſiege ſerveth as a fair excuſe, which I think beſt (if you think
good) to continue until opportunity ſerve to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute our deſign, and in
the mean time to remain as Neuter.</p>
            <p>I know well <hi>Clerio</hi> (ſaid <hi>Lozia</hi>) that you have
a courage and underſtanding admirable; go forward with your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign;
<hi>Lozia,</hi> and what means ſhe can procure, ſhall aſſiſt your
ambition, even to the end. Having ſaid thus, and having tears in her eyes,
ſhe further ſaid. <hi>Clerio</hi> my friend, I pray write to me often, to
the end that being deprived of your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, <pb n="145" facs="tcp:115129:77"/>I have
your ſpirit continually before my eyes. She then called the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle man who
came from the King of <hi>Spain</hi> and ſaid to him; Sir, go with the
General of my army, and treat with him, for a young Maid as I am, cannot
under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the mannaging of affaires, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the King that I am his
moſt humble Servant. This Gentleman took leave of <hi>Lozia,</hi> and went to
the Army with <hi>Clerio,</hi> who ſo ſoon as he was arived, writ this
Letter to the King of <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>YOur Majeſtie hath not a more affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ſervant in this
Kingdome then I am, who never had ſo much ſorrow for any thing as that I
cannot testifie it in ſo good an occaſion, ſo ſoon as I deſire, my
honour &amp; the good of my Miſtreſs do ſo much depend on this Siege,
which I cannot raiſe unleſs I loſe one or the other: But ſoon after the
ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of this town, which will be ſuddainly as <pb n="146" facs="tcp:115129:78"/>I
think, I have commandment to go finde your Majeſty, to render to you all the
good ſervices I ſhall be worthy of.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours, CLERIO.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>When the King had read this excuſe, he was angred;
nevertheleſs the hope which he had of ſoon having this aid, did extreamly
content him.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the <hi>Engliſh</hi> loſt no time; for he
ſurpriſed places, he beſieg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed good towns, became Maſter of the field,
and ſent new Embaſſadors to <hi>Clerio,</hi> with fair and rich
preſents to deſire his Company. <hi>Clerio</hi> returned them this
an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer:</p>
            <p>Sirs, I cannot honeſtly fight againſt my King, this duty
hinders me to enter into League with you, but however I will not refuſe the
affection of ſo great a Queen as is yours; you ſee that ſix thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
men are not ſufficient to take this town, and with the twenty thouſand more
which remain, I ſhall but incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate your Army: Nevertheleſs I 
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:115129:78"/>promiſe you not to remove any thing until I have taken
it, which will not be ſuddainly; and then I ſhall ſee what I have to
do.</p>
            <p>Theſe men being thus ſatisfied, retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to their General,
who was very glad that <hi>Clerio</hi> ſhewed himſelf to be indiffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent.
In this time <hi>Clerio's</hi> Lacquies never left carrying of Letters between
him and <hi>Lozia,</hi> and if they all gave conſolation to her minde, yet
one proved unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, for a bullet of a Cannon flew a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the window of
<hi>Clerio's</hi> Chamber, and killed a Gentleman, whoſe bones gave
<hi>Clerio</hi> ſuch a blow, that he fel down for dead as he was a writing to
his Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs. The Lacquey ſeeing what had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, took the letter
half written, and carried it with this ſad news to <hi>Lozia,</hi> who being
wholly tranſported to ſee this Paper, took it of him, and before ſhe had
read it, being impatient asked of him, if <hi>Clerio</hi> were dead: who
anſwered yes, at this word ſhe fell down in a ſwoon; <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia</hi>
preſently ſent away the Lacquey, and took ſo great care of her
Miſtreſs, that <pb n="148" facs="tcp:115129:79"/>ſhe brought her to her ſences in a
quarter of an hour; when ſhe read theſe words which <hi>Clerio</hi> had
written:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>FAir Princeſs, you could not more honor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably renderme ſlave
to a thouſand and a thouſand amorous wiſhes, of the beauties and graces
which Heaven and Nature hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on your ſoul and Viſige, then in
making me Leader of ſo fair an army; who having the honor to command it, am
depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a thouſand times in a day, of the honor to obey you: So full of
diſpleaſure and love, Fair one I die.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>At theſe laſt words, ſhe cryed out, Oh diſaſtrous
<hi>Lozia!</hi> (then being inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted with a violent grief, ſhe loſt her
ſpeech which love ſoon made rendition of unto her:) <hi>Lozia,</hi> no, but
the miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt living, ſeeing that in a moment thou haſt loſt the
poſſeſſion of the gallanteſt Cavaleer in the world; whom Nature had
formed the moſt perfect and moſt reſerved that ſhe had to render an
amor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous marvel of Virtue and Honor; <hi>Clerio,</hi> 
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:115129:79"/>dare
I any more in this misfortune pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce this fair name, which I religiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
honor? who in his life time hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me a thouſand ſweet deaths: and in
his honorable deaths, a thouſand unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py lives. O my eyes, weep until your
cold tears of grief extinguiſh with my life their deadly flames, which have
ſometimes ſerved as fire of joy to honor at houſand and a thouſand
amorous tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs, which you have made of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and heart of this brave
one. Then ſhe transformd theſe their amorous mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal parols into ſighs
and tears.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vincia</hi> on the other ſide cryed bitterly for the loſs
of her Couſin, and had much ado to keep her ſelf from ſwooning; but ſhe
knowing that her Miſtreſs had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther comforter but her, did earneſtly
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat her to have patience.</p>
            <p>Ah <hi>Vincia</hi> (ſaid <hi>Lozia</hi>) am not I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy, to
have innocently ſought for the death of him, who with the perils of his life
hath preſerved mine, from the hands of this cruel Tyrant, who is the cauſe
of my ill hap?</p>
            <pb n="150" facs="tcp:115129:80"/>
            <p>Wherefore do not I go into ſome cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the world, to waſte
away the reſt of my days? <hi>Vincia,</hi> read a little this let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, where
you ſhall ſee an incredible a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous paſſion; and theſe laſt words
which ſerve as a propheſie for our il hap. At this inſtant ſhe heard
ſome knock at the door; Is not their yet enough ſaid ſhe, what ill
fortune? <hi>Vincia</hi> aroſe, and ſhe had hardly opened the door, when
<hi>Lozia</hi> eſpying a Gentleman of <hi>Clerio's,</hi> ſaid to him, my
friend, your Maſter is dead, and I ſee him dead in dying. Dead! (ſaid he)
Madam, behold a letter of his which he hath commanded me to bring to you. What
is not <hi>Clerio</hi> dead? (ſaid <hi>Lozia</hi>) No Madam (God be thanked)
(ſaid he) he was onely a little aſtoniſhed at the blow: and for fear you
ſhould be fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he hath expreſly ſent me to you, to aſſure you
that he is well. Is not <hi>Clerio</hi> dead! (ſaid <hi>Lozia</hi>) ought I
or can I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve it: <hi>Vincia</hi> is it poſſible? Madam (ſaid ſhe)
you have more reaſon to give credit to a Gentleman then to a Lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quey.</p>
            <pb n="151" facs="tcp:115129:80"/>
            <p>Then this great Princeſs being tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with pleaſure,
caſt her ſelf on the neck of this Gentleman and kiſſed him: but ſhe
ſoon came to herſelf, and excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her ſelf with theſe ſpeeches;
Now my friend thou maiſt report that thou haſt had a kiſs of
<hi>Lozia,</hi> in recompence of ſo profitable news, whereon depends the
conſervation of my State: and then taking the Letter ſhe read it, the words
whereof were theſe.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>FAir Princeſs, I think that this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man will have need of
confeſsion in the other world, who hath failed after his death to make a
cruel homicide. I had a thouſand times more lamented the life of a world of
innocent loves (which I hold in poſſeſsing your graces and fair eys) then
mine: whoſe loſs would have been as honorable as happy for your ſervice:
But it ſeems that the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens have been willing in my preſervation, to
witneſs more good then in my loſs. No ill bath happened unto me in this
ſtrange acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, (God be thanked) but only my arm a little hurt, which in
two days will be capable <pb n="152" facs="tcp:115129:81"/>to give three blows with a
ſword for your ſake; this abſence is nothing elſe but an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect
table of my memory, which in the mid<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dle of my moſt pleaſant and deſired
dotings, repreſents the beſt that it can, your ſpirit, your beauties and
your graces, where I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipher a thouſand times in a day, my moſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
and moſt amorous conceptions.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>CLERIO.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Vincia</hi> led this Gentleman into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther chamber, to give
him the collation, and time to her Miſtreſs, to make theſe new regrets.
<hi>Lozia</hi> (quoth ſhe) how ſoon an alteration hath this unlooked for
news cauſed in my breaſt! <hi>Vincia</hi> having ſpent ſome time with
the Gentleman, returned with him unto <hi>Lozia,</hi> who ſaid to him: Sir, I
pray you tell <hi>Clerio</hi> that I am ſo lazy that I know not how to write
to him; and I pray let him not know that I was informed of his death: let him
ſend me word in what eſtate the Army is in, if he hopes to take the town
ſoon or no, or if he needs any thing. The Gentleman departed and went to his
Maſter, who <pb n="315" facs="tcp:115129:81"/>had planted his Cannons in the Trench. In
the mean time the Engliſh executed his affairs ſo well, that he had already
poſſeſſed himſelf of the third part of Spain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clerio</hi> fearing that the number of pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces would render
him ſo ſtrong, and his often victories ſo redoubtable, that it would be
hard to defeat him; ſet upon his own enemies ſo rigorouſly, that in eight
days he conſtrained the Inhabitants to yeeld the Town to him, becauſe they
would not be pillaged; and the Duke of <hi>Blanfort</hi> who began to
premeditate of his flight, was ſo aſtoniſhed at his riſing to ſee
ſo great a number beſiege his houſ, that he had pains enough in the
midſt of ſo many perils, to make choyce of the leaſt; and all the
ambition of this poor Prince was, in the ballancing of his life and honor,
metamorphoſed in a baſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be ſlave to his enemy, and ſerve
as a triumph to him, into whoſe hands he might with the loſs of his honor,
hope for ſome aſſurance of his miſerable life. Theſe cogitations
having poſſeſſed him, <pb n="154" facs="tcp:115129:82"/>he reſolved to yeeld,
which he did; and being brought to the Army, <hi>Clerio</hi> hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtly
received him; and having him at his ſide he entred as a glorious Maſter of
the Town and Governor. So ſoon as he had appointed a ſufficient Garriſon
of Souldiers therein, and left money to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair the ruines thereof he departed,
and led the Duke to his Miſtreſs to abide her doom. This fair Princeſs
was at that time as much poſſeſſed with choller as joy, to ſee her
ſpouſe and her enemy, the one ful of honor and glory, and the other of
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain and ſhame; to whom ſhe ſaid theſe words. I wonder that I
ſee you in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place then on a Scaffold wicked one as thou art, who
haſt dared to enterpriſe on my perſon; and practiſed a Rebellion in my
eſtate: but aſſure thy ſelf that I will be revenged of thy
perfidiouſnes with ſo much juſtice, and the ſubject which I have, that
I will render thee the miſerableſt that ever was; if thou doſt not
between this and to morrow, yeeld up all the places which thou holdeſt, I
will cruelly kill thee. Then turning her <pb n="155" facs="tcp:115129:82"/>ſelf towards
<hi>Clerio</hi> ſhe ſaid. I pray take this man from my preſence, his only
ſight puts me into extream choller, and above all things in the world have a
care that he be ſtrictly guarded. He would have ſpoken but the Princeſs
becauſe ſhe would not hear him, went from thence into another chamber to
entertain <hi>Clerio,</hi> who went unto her and remained with her all that
night, and had remained there all his life time in ſuch agreeable delight, if
<hi>Mars</hi> (at his riſing) had not placed a ſword at his ſide to go
combate the proud Engliſh, who already thought themſelves Maſters of
Spain, whoſe whole hopes of liberty was ſtaid in the onely valour of
<hi>Clerio,</hi> who having be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged the beſt place which they had with
forty peeces of Ordnance and 30000. footmen, ſtaid not there but eight dayes
before it was delivered; and thus continuing his ſieges and Victories, he
took one by one all the Towns which the Engliſh held, alwayes leaving the
field free. When he had placed Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the places which he had taken,
he <pb n="156" facs="tcp:115129:83"/>took the field and purſued the Engliſh ſo
quickly, that he conſtrained them to fight, and they had no ſooner given
Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail but they loſt it, where poor <hi>Don Allio</hi> was ſlain, who
deſpairing in his love, had not above two hours before ſent a Letter to his
Miſtreſs.</p>
            <p>This happie Victory gave ſo much reputation to <hi>Clerio,</hi>
fear to his Enemie and jealouſie to the Spaniard, that the one fled, and the
other aſſured himſelf of his ſuſpicion. The apprehenſion of death
could not give the Engliſh ſo ſwift wings to ſave themſelves, as the
ambition and honour of <hi>Clerio</hi> to take them. And becauſe I ſhall be
too long in deſcribing the Armes, the Horſes, the ſpoyles, and money
which the Souldiers gained, it ſhall ſuffice to tell you that this glorious
happy vanquiſher lead the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral to the fair <hi>Lozia,</hi> who at one
time made two ſuperbous Triumphs of van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſher and vanquiſhed. This fair
Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs who deſired nothing ſo much as the honour of <hi>Clerio,</hi>
left all to his diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and he who had more ambition 
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:115129:83"/>then avarice, in ſtead of placing him in ſurety in
ſome ſtrong Hold, and treat of Ranſome, ſaid to him; Sir, fortune hath
given me enough advantage over you without my ſearching any new ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of
affliction, if your Souldiers had had as much courage as you, I had been very
like to be in the ſame danger; I pray you do not think that I detain you here
as a priſoner of War, but as one of my very good friends, and in ſtead of
Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome I onely ask yours and your Queens favour: your ſhiping are all
ſeparated and loſt, but when you think good to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part you ſhall command
mine. This Lord was ſo aſtoniſhed at this French courteſie, that after
he had made a million of offers of ſervice he extreamly thanked him, and
advowed that it appertained to none but <hi>Clerio</hi> to oblige the Queen and
him for this unparalleld favour; and after he had kiſſed the hands of the
Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs <hi>Lozia,</hi> he embarqued with a world of fair preſents which
were given him.</p>
            <p>Whilſt he makes his Voyage let us <pb n="158" facs="tcp:115129:84"/>return to
the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> who attended for <hi>Clerio</hi> to redeliver
thoſe places which he had taken, and for that purpoſe he ſent a
Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man unto him to treat about this affaire: but <hi>Clerio</hi> who
dream'd of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs then the rendition of them, made this anſwer.</p>
            <p>Sir, I know not why the King hath ſo much diſtruſt of the
fidelity and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which I have ſworn to his ſervice. I think that I
have given him a ſufficient teſtimony, having ruined ſo powerful an
enemy, who every day (as you know) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired me to joyn with him, offering me
the moyety of all that we ſhould pretend to: but (God be thanked) I never had
a will to do ſo great a diſſervice to my Prince. I think it ſtrange,
that having had this cogniſance, he thinks me not capable to conſerve
thoſe Towns which I have been worthy to take. I cannot ſuffer it, that
taking from me the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of theſe places, he gives the honour of my
honour to another, which I have merited with the peril of my life, 
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:115129:84"/>and all my friends, who I think will not depart, although
I pray them; for their entertainment ſerves in recompence of the good
ſervices which they have done to his Majeſty under my conduct: I humbly
pray you Sir to repreſent to the King all theſe rational Reaſons, and
aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure him of my moſt humble ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
            <p>This Gentleman being departed went to the King, who having heard
this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, entred into councel to know what courſe was beſt to be
taken: ſome were of advice to declare war againſt him, others to go ſeize
on him, but one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them who was more ſage then the reſt ſpake in
this manner.</p>
            <p>Sir, Seeing that your Majeſty hath done me the honour to confide
in me, I ſhould think my ſelf culpable of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand invincible crimes
if I ſhould wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from my opinion to flatter you. <hi>Clerio</hi> hath done
a great good to your Kingdom, what ſubject ſoever hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him, as a
cloſe Enemy, that feare and peril are leſſer, then if we had the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, 
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:115129:85"/>who might have had continual ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies from the Queen
his Miſtreſs. <hi>Clerio</hi> is in your Countrey, who we can eaſily
render odious, he hath no ſtrange alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance: I plainly ſee that he dares
not declare vvar againſt you, attending for ſome ſlight pretence which
you will put into his hands, with which he will ſo effectually ſerve
himſelf, having a fair and puiſlant Army, a quantity of places, and means,
that he will cauſe a great trouble to your Kingdom, and a very great
wearineſs to your Majeſty. If he had once given this beginning to his
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and blur to his ambition, he would become ſo extreamly odious,
that your Kingdom would not ſuffer him: fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, his Army
ſtrengthening daily by his fortune, the King of <hi>France,</hi> (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
there is a League between you) would ſecretly aſſiſt him. This
weaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of your Eſtate Sir, would give cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to your Enemies,
diſobedience in your Subjects, and happineſs to <hi>Clerio,</hi> who hath
already a beginning good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough.</p>
            <pb n="177" facs="tcp:115129:85"/>
            <p>Likewiſe, if as your Servant he hath worthily ſerved you, you
will do him a great affront in taking from him thoſe places which he hath (in
a manner) made conqueſt of, to give the glory of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to another: this
will offend him ſo much, that he will have a lawful excuſe to make war
againſt you. You are ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provided of men and money, you ought to take
this into conſideration. My ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice is, that your Majeſty let things alone
in the eſtate they are in, until your Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels come from the
<hi>Indies,</hi> you will by little and little augment your Army, and then it
will be a ſeaſonable time to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of him what part he holdeth.</p>
            <p>Although theſe reaſons were fair and profitable, yet could
they not hinder the Kings declaring war againſt <hi>Clerio,</hi> (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
it was but coldly) who becauſe he would not give bad impreſſions of his
ambition, dared not to encounter with him, but deſired nothing ſo
impatiently, as to vanquiſh in defending himſelf, which was as eaſie for
him to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh, as it was for a ſtrong Man to beat <pb n="178" facs="tcp:115129:86"/>a ſick man, who offends him more through malice then force. He
ſoon drew his Army out of Gariſons, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiedged <hi>Madrid,</hi> in
ſuch manner that no Victualls could be carried therein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</p>
            <p>The people who were impatient, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves among ſo
many continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all alarm's, their hands, their teeth, and their ſhops
unprofitable, asked for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more then to place theſe people from their
former exerciſes, to agree their Prince with <hi>Clerio,</hi> and peace with
their ſtomacks, who had not digeſted war: The King fearing ſome
ſedition or revolt, was perſwaded by his Councel, and forced by
neceſſity to demand truce of <hi>Clerio,</hi> who dared not to refuſe it,
leaſt his Arms ſhould be reputed more tyranous then juſt. They therefore
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed on a truce for ſix moneths, each of them deſigning ſo well
(whilſt it ſhould laſt) to prepare their buſineſs that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
ended, he might eaſily tryumph over his enemy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clerio</hi> went ſoon after to ſee his fair 
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:115129:86"/>
               <hi>Lozia</hi> (being accompanied with an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
Train) who kindly welcomed him. Whilſt he was in this Company, he reſolved
to make his publique wedding; And for that cauſe he ſent a Gentleman to the
King, to intreat him to do him the honour to be preſent: And although he was
much angred thereat, yet he ſeemed to be glad: and becauſe he would obliege
him further, he went vvith all his Court. Great was the reſort thither of
Ladies &amp; Knights, and at the Kings entrance there was a fair Tragedy,
whoſe ſubject I will be tacent of. When he was arived, <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zia</hi>
after many humble ſalutations, and reſpectful embracements, ſaid to
him.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> Although the valor and merits of <hi>Clerio</hi>
render him worthy, not only to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouſe me, but the greateſt Princes in
the World: nevertheleſs, by reaſon that he is a ſtranger, and hath not
the quality of a Prince, which is rather left to us, then ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by us: I
know that you will think it ſtrange that I have contracted ſecret
ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony with him, and that reported, hath <pb n="180" facs="tcp:115129:87"/>gone to have
been with <hi>Vincia,</hi> But Sir, you know that being under the tyrannical
ſubjection of the Duke of <hi>Blantfort,</hi> and honoured with the honour I
had to apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to you, I could not at that time do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe: I am glad
that his fortune and courage have rendred him ſo great, that he deſerveth
one of my quality, and that my e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection be worthy of my love.</q>
            <p>The King in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupting her, ſaid to her, Couſin, it is better
to be Son of fortune, then of a Prince; and embraſing <hi>Clerio,</hi> he
ſaid to him, <hi>Couſin,</hi> I will be at your nuptials, and beleeve me
that I make as of you, that I eſteem your alliance more then of the
greateſt Monarch in the World. <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio</hi> after he had moſt humbly
thanked him for the honour which he did him, ſaid to him,</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> Your Majeſty obliges me ſo much, to render you
ſervice, that there ſhall not be a day in all my life, wherein I ſhall
not have the ſame deſire. I very well know that I am unworthy of the honour
of your alliance, and that not I alone but the greateſt of this Kingdom:
therefore I ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hold this good fortune of fortune, and <pb n="181" facs="tcp:115129:87"/>your favour, rather then of any thing in the World. But ſeeing that
the Heavens and you render me worthy of this good, I will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to render
my ſelf ſo agreeable and profitable to your Majeſty, that you ſhall
ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have cauſe to repent you ſelf of doing me this Honour.</q>
            <p>After theſe ſpeeches the Company aſſembled, and were
aſſiſtant at the eſpouſals of <hi>Clerio</hi> and <hi>Lozia,</hi> and
<hi>Clerio</hi> left nothing undon that might conduce to the contentation and
pleaſure of theſe fair Ladies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clerio</hi> was ſo pleaſed with the honour of ſo
agreeable Hoſteſſes, theſe fair La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and the King of <hi>Spain</hi>
in theſe deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious paſtimes, that the one would not have been wearied with
theſe magnifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent expences, nor the other with receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo good
entertainment, if the Eſtates had not called the King away to practiſe an
ill office to him who had made them ſo welcom. His departure gave ſuch a
trouble to this amorous Aſſembly, that I cannot repreſent unto you the
ſighs and ſad tears which this harſh and mortal ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration gave to the
hearts and eyes of <pb n="182" facs="tcp:115129:88"/>thoſe who poſſeſſed the
favours of their Miſtreſſes, nor the ſighs of hope which others had of
this good. This is a Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Love, which love himſelf repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented,
whilſt that they were a drying up of tears for ſo ſad a departure; let us
return to <hi>Lozia,</hi> who now dares call <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio</hi> her Husband, whom
ſhe before called her Knight, her Servant and General of her Army. This young
Cavalier was now exalted to the top of fortune, who but lately was but an
ordinary Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, &amp; now he dared to claim one of the richeſt and
faireſt Ladies and Princeſſes in all the World to be his Lady and
e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpouſed Wife. Soon after this the King prepared his Army for the field,
and <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio</hi> was no whit idle in the mean time; but having made fit
preparations for war, met the King his enemy in the field, many bloody fights
and encounters were daily, which I ſhall omit; but only thus much I ſhall
inform you of, that in one fight, our brave victorious Champion, not only
ſubdued his enemies, but hand to hand encountred the King and led him 
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:115129:88"/>away priſoner in deſpight of all his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, &amp;
won the field &amp; day. <hi>Clerio</hi> having the King at his pleaſure and
mercy, ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by that means to mak a baſe peace, or to get treaſure for
his Ranſom; but ſhewing his heroick mind and diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he freely
and in ſafety ſent him away into his own Camp. But this perfidious
trayterous King conceived ſuch hatred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Clerio,</hi> that he
reſolved to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged not openly, but with a Revolt and ſecret
Treaſon, he having ſecretly given monies into the hands of that perfideous
<hi>Spaniſh</hi> Nation, in ſuch a manner, that one day all the places,
Holds, and Forts that <hi>Clerio</hi> had in his profeſſion revolted and
declared againſt him, except that which he had taken from the Duke of
<hi>Blantfort:</hi> the Souldiers that were gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſoned there being
Gaſcoigns, who ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther looked to their honour then wealth. Thus poor
<hi>Clerio</hi> was taken with ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looked for treaſon, that he had no
ſooner the poſſeſſion then the knowledg of his ill hap, neither had
he time to remedy it, but only he reſolved rather to die (in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending 
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:115129:89"/>himſelf and his Lady) honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, then to yield to the
mercy of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſs enemy. <hi>Lozia</hi> having had the cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſance of
this ill hap, was amazed at the novelty, and aſtoniſhed with fear, not for
the loſs of her eſtate and life, but for that of <hi>Clerio,</hi> who ſhe
was ſure, was of ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danted a ſpirit and courage, that he would rather
die then let his honour die, or diminiſh one jot in yielding himſelf to his
enemy: wherefore ſhe made all haſte poſſible to the place where he was,
ſhe found him in a ſharp diſpute with his enemies, maintaining with the
point of his Sword, and all conquering and invinſible Arm, a breach which his
enemies had made in the wall; reſolving rather to leave his life in the
place, then ſuffer any of thoſe perfideous Currs to enter therein. But
<hi>Lozia's</hi> coming hindred him of his deſign; for ſhe ſo far
prevailed with him, that ſhe drew him (although unwillingly) from the place,
and afterwards made ſuch lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and pitiful ſpeeches to him, that he
whoſe courage was not to be overmaſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <pb n="185" facs="tcp:115129:89"/>with the
ſword of the braveſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, was now wholly ſubdued, van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed, and
conquered by her teares, in ſuch manner that for grief he ſwooned in the
place, ſhe taking this oppertuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſoon conveyed him a Ship-board, and
having provided her ſelf ſufficiently with Jewels and treaſure embarqued
likewiſe with <hi>Vincia</hi> and ſome others, and having a fair wind
preſently ſet ſail, leaving the Town to the mercy of this mercileſs and
cruel enemy. The Ship had ſailed a good ſpace of time ere <hi>Clerio</hi>
recovered his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; but when he had recollected himſelf, and
underſtood how all things had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, he much wondred at ſo ſuddain an
alteration, and being much angred and tormented with himſelf, he complained
againſt his fortune and deſtinies, and was enraged to think that he
ſhould in ſo ſad a condition leave his fellow Souldiers, who had ſo
bravely and reſolutely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended his fortune and their own. But
<hi>Lozia</hi> who with her charms was at any time able to ſubdue him, did at
laſt ſo far prevail that ſhe made him reſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented 
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:115129:90"/>in outward appearance, though not inwardly in his mind,
and now the ſhip having ſailed ſometime, they began to conſider what
part it was beſt for them to take. <hi>Clerio</hi> knowing that
<hi>Lozia</hi> had ſo well provided for wealth reſolved to ſpend the
reſt of his life in peace and tranquility, and to that intent and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,
he commanded that they ſhould ſail directly towards the great River
<hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> which place was then inhabited by Chriſtians, they had not
long continued in this their courſe, but they eſpied Land, which cauſed
gladneſs and joy to ſpring in their hearts. The Ship being come near the
ſhoar, <hi>Clerio</hi> commanded the Ordnance that were in the ſhip
ſhould be diſcharged, which made ſuch a reſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Eccho in thoſe
parts, that the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants flocked to the Sea ſide, that they might
underſtand the cauſe of this ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain a novelty, where they were no
ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er arived, but they might ſee our Hero and Heroeſſe landing, and
they were ſo ſtricken in admiration at ſo raviſhing a proſpect, as
was that of <hi>Lozia,</hi> that they <pb n="187" facs="tcp:115129:90"/>thought the Gods and
Goddeſſes were come to viſit them; but they ſoon chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their
opinions, having had the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to hear the Tongues of <hi>Lozia</hi> and
<hi>Clerio</hi> ſpeak to them. Theſe Inhabitants ſeeing the courteous
demeanor of theſe new come ſtrangers, offering them all their
aſſiſtance in helping their neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but they kindly thanked
them. Theſe ſtrangers being now come, <hi>Clerio</hi> with all expedition
cauſed workmen to build a fair Palace, wherein he and his beauteous Lady
might conſummate the remaining parts of their lives, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing built, they
paſſed their time therein, entertaining themſelves alwayes with their
loves, and they cauſed little win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows to be made, whereby they might have a
proſpect to <hi>Nilus,</hi> and other Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and Iſlands there adjoyning.
And thus in the middle of theſe delights, they deliciouſly paſſed away
many years, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from vanity, fear, and ambition, receiving more
pleaſure in their misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, and in the poſſeſſion of ſo little
Land, then they ever had in their try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs, <pb n="188" facs="tcp:115129:91"/>victories,
and happy ſucceſs, with a world of good fortune. Here was a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual
Melody of Birds, and all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights that a Rural Habitation could
af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clerio</hi> would have ended his dayes in theſe loves, if
<hi>Mars</hi> jealous of his good had not raiſed the <hi>Turk</hi> againſt
the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> but honour and Religion obliged him to defend them,
they having choſen him for their Captain &amp; Leader. This un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy War
ſnatched him from the arms of his fair <hi>Lozia,</hi> who being extreamly
afflicted at his reſolution, took him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, and uſed many
perſwaſions to cauſe him not to go through with his enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize; but he
conſidering that his honour and Religion depended chiefly thereon, would by
no means condeſcend to her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, but having given her a thouſand
Kiſſes and ſweet loving embraces, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from her, leaving her to
her ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudes, and leaving for her comfort her Damſel <hi>Vincia,</hi> who
for the ſake of her Couſin <hi>Clerio</hi> enterprized any thing to conduce
to his happineſs and good, and <pb n="189" facs="tcp:115129:91"/>to remove her
Miſtreſs from ſolitarineſs, uſing all the comfortable expreſſions
that her capacity afforded her. Whilſt <hi>Vincia</hi> and <hi>Lozia</hi>
remained at home, <hi>Clerio</hi> gave battel abroad to his enemies, which
added ſuch luſter to his perſon in that he alwayes remained Conqueror and
Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the field, that in few dayes his va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor gave an incredible
reputation to the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and an extream fear to the Hearts of
theſe <hi>Barbarians.</hi> Alwayes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing his Victory and fortune, he
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained Maſter of the field, Cities and Towns were rendred to him, ſome
voluntarily, ſome through fear, and others by ſiege: he founded
Hoſpitalls, inſtituted Religions, and builded Churches. The
<hi>Chriſtians</hi> had kept the Levant in the knowledg of God, and under
their authority even unto the end of the World, if they had not been defeated
by themſelves, with a fooliſh ambition, which gave advantage to the
<hi>Turks,</hi> who having an unequal number, ſoon vanquiſhed his
enemies.</p>
            <p>This happened between two <hi>Lords,</hi> 
               <pb n="190" facs="tcp:115129:92"/>who
having like command in the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Army during the abſence of
<hi>Clerio,</hi> who was gone to viſit his Miſtreſs. One of theſe was
ſo wicked and perfideous, that he turned <hi>Turk,</hi> and revenged
him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf on his own ſoul, and all the <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> together.</p>
            <p>This Treaſon was ſo utilious to this Barbarian, and ſo
prejudicial to ours, that he eaſily defeated the Armies, and in the midſt
of this diſorder, retook the Towns.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clerio</hi> being filled with courage and deſpair, could not
put order to ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed a confuſion, and do he what he could, he could
not poſſibly gather toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther above ten thouſand men, who with ſo good
a Leader performed their parts ſo well, that the Enemy was greatly
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated. He gained one Battel where he took the <hi>Baſſa,</hi> and
with this handful of men performed a world of gallantries. The <hi>Turk</hi>
ſeeing the courage and fortune of <hi>Clerio,</hi> raiſed another Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of
100000 men, and preſſed ſo near to <hi>Clerio,</hi> that he foreed him to
fight, <pb n="191" facs="tcp:115129:92"/>where he and his were vanquiſhed with victory,
having all the day long killed ſo many, that their wearineſs was the
cauſe of their defeat, not the valor of theſe Doggs. <hi>Clerio</hi> yet
rallied 1000. or 1200 men, who for his laſt refuge he carried to his houſe.
This Tyrant followed him, beſieged him, and ſet him ſo furiouſly, that
if his courage, by his often ſcouting forth, had not ſomewhat hindred them,
they had taken it that very ſame day. The next day this <hi>Turk</hi> renewed
this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault, and at laſt made a breach where the poor Princeſs
<hi>Lozia</hi> being no leſs cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious then amourous, kept Company with
<hi>Clerio</hi> all the day on the breach, and defeated as many enemies with
the ſweet admiration of her beauty, as <hi>Clerio</hi> with the bloody blowes
of his Sword. But theſe two Lovers being in the end weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with their ill
hap, went a little to reſt themſelves on a Bed, to gain ſome new
ſtrength to their now feebled force, in this ſweet ſleep they ſuffered
the mortal Criſes of their lives and fortunes: for the enemy perſued them
ſo ſudainly, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <pb n="202" facs="tcp:115129:93"/>gained the baſs Court of
the Caſtle, he would within two hours have been Maſter thereof. But the god
<hi>Cupid</hi> thinking that their ſhame would have been his, let looſe his
wings, and carrying the poyſon with him, (wherein he was wont to temper his
mortal darts) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented it to <hi>Vincia,</hi> and ſaid to her,</p>
            <p>My friend, if you love ſo much as you ought the honour of your
Couſin, and this fair Princeſs, put this Nectar in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their mouthes, which
the gods have ſent them to render them immortal, to the end, that by this
means they may be freed from this Tyrant. You ſhall in one inſtant ſee
them ſo divine and ſo fair, that in the twinkling of an eye, they will
va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh from theſe barbarous Troops, as Clouds from the ſight of ſo
clear and divine Beams. <hi>Vincia</hi> being as much ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed with the
beauty of this fair Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger, as perſwaded with his perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
and deſired deſires, imagining her ſelf to be already ſome little Saint
in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice of theſe looked for deities, took this ſole diſſolving
poyſon from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful <pb n="193" facs="tcp:115129:93"/>hands of love, and with hers
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing innocent put it to their lips.</p>
            <p>Theſe two Lovers feeling the mortal effects of this poyſon, at
one time both awaked, and after a thouſand kiſſes and dear imbracements,
<hi>Clerio</hi> finding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf at the end of his fortunes and life, took
his leave of <hi>Lozia</hi> in many ſad and dolful ſpeeches, and calling
for his Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen he ſaid to them. Sirs, excuſe me I intreat you, If I
have not yet done any thing for you to diſingage me from the obligation which
I owe you, it very much grieves my ſoul: come I pray you that I may embrace
you, and take with this my laſt adieu all my money and jewels. Go my friends
treat with this Barbarian for the conſervation of your lives and eſtates,
and for the honor of your Maſter who dies.</p>
            <p>Theſe poor Gentlemen retired in tears and ſighs not having
power to ſpeak one word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clerio</hi> hearing the ſighs of his Couſin, and the
juſt reproaches which ſhe gave to Love, for having ſo cruelly deceived 
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:115129:94"/>her; comforted her with loving ſpeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, but ſhe
refuſing all comfort reſolved to die with them, and therefore ſhe took
the reſt of that portion which remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that <hi>Clerio</hi> and
<hi>Lozia</hi> had not drunk.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lozia</hi> likewiſe finding her ſelf ready to expire,
turned towards <hi>Clerio</hi> and gave many a pittiful ſigh, and uttered
many words in tears, and at laſt embrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another in their arms, and
both making a ſigh at one time, theſe two ſouls confuſedly carried on
the wings of one ſigh went to the Eliſian fields, where Love who attended
them in the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of a thouſand and a thouſand Lovers went before them,
and with honor gave them the honor of the moſt honorable place, as they who
were moſt worthy. A thouſand Crowns honored their heads, a thouſand Loves
their Loves, and a thouſand Triumphs their Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Let us here leave
theſe two Lovers in their new delights, and come to <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia,</hi> who
having perceived this mortal ſeperation, embraced <hi>Clerio</hi> and
<hi>Lozia,</hi> a thouſand times one after another, and <pb n="195" facs="tcp:115129:94"/>in the middle of theſe tears and ſighs, drew theſe ſpeeches
from her heart, with moſt impatient paſſions of her ſoul.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clerio</hi> art thou dead? And thou fair <hi>Lozia?</hi> Alas,
I yet feel ſome warmth on their amorous cheeks! Your fair ſouls, have they
already left theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect beauties, which the heavens and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture jealous
of this fair work, jealouſly honor? Alas! muſt I cloſe theſe fair eys,
which amorouſly kills after death thoſe who have the honor to ſee them;
and this dilicate mouth, which with a thouſand fair diſcourſes,
ſeaſoned with the grace and ſweetneſs of ſpeech, anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mateth ſouls
with raviſhment? Fair hands, muſt mine render yours this laſt office of
duty and affection, cloſing you under this ſheet, with all the beauties and
graces together? Alas! pardon me for your death fair Miſtreſs, which I have
innocently procured; by the artifice and treaſon of this Perfidious: But I do
ill to accuſe him, it was not reaſonable that this royal Majeſty, theſe
beauties, theſe ſweet, theſe prety, theſe amorous mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers 
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:115129:95"/>ſhould ſerve for a Trophy to this <hi>Barbarian,</hi>
who to honour his Trophies, would have publickly diſhonoured them: and to the
end, that my eyes may loſe the honour of ſeeing you, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing theirs
alſo in the middle of theſe tenebroſities, fair one I follow you; and
pronounſing theſe ſpeeches, ſhe fell down dead at the feet of the fair
<hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this mean time, the <hi>Turk</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with theſe
Gentlemen what they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired: and knowing that <hi>Clerio</hi> and
<hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zia</hi> were ſick, had yet this reſpect (in deſpight of his
cruclties) that he cauſed the fattery to ceaſe, and he made this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
to thoſe who brought him the news of their death, demanding permiſſion to
build a monument to bury then in.</p>
            <p>I will not refuſe this honour to ſo great a Prince and his
Wife; but I will ſpend one hundred thouſand Crowns to render them worthy
the braveſt Cavalier and the faireſt Princeſs that ever was, and 
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:115129:95"/>I would it had coſt me two millions that they had
lived.</p>
            <p>He entred into the Caſtle, and ſeeing <hi>Clerio</hi> and
<hi>Lozia</hi> under a Cloth of Gold, covered with a ſheet, he commanded that
they ſhould be uncovered, and after he had honoured the memory of the valor
and merits of this Prince, turning his eyes on the fair Body of <hi>Lozia,</hi>
he one by one looked over her beauties and Graces, who ſeemed rather to be in
a ſweet ſleep of love then death, which this barbarous heart received with
one thouſand regrets, and two thouſand ſo living ſighs, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo
mortal flames, that he ſerved as a victim to himſelf to expiate his
cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            <p>The tears and ſighs of the vanquiſhers and vanquiſhed, were
in ſuch manner mingled together that grief and victory were equal in their
inequality. In this time the workmen finiſhed the Tombe which was of
<hi>Jaſper,</hi> mingled with Pearls and precious ſtones, ſo fair and
ſo rich, that better could not be, where theſe <pb n="198" facs="tcp:115129:96"/>Gentlemen with a thouſand ſighs, and a thouſand tears,
honourably buried <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia</hi> and <hi>Clerio,</hi> and the fair
<hi>Lozia.</hi> Fait <hi>Ladies,</hi> let us leave theſe Gentlemen in their
Voyage, and theſe <hi>Levers</hi> in their reſt.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Na. Brent.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>May 8.
1652.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:115129:96"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
